<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royall exchange to suche worshipfull citezins, marchants, gentlemen and other occupiers of the contrey as resorte therevnto. Try to retaine, or send back agayne. The contents ys after the preface. Sene and allowed here.</title>
            <author>Payne, John, fl. 1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102533</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1111:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Royall exchange to suche worshipfull citezins, marchants, gentlemen and other occupiers of the contrey as resorte therevnto. Try to retaine, or send back agayne. The contents ys after the preface. Sene and allowed here.</title>
                  <author>Payne, John, fl. 1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed wth Gulis Romaen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In Harlem :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.XCVII [1597]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: John Payne.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Christian exhortation.</note>
                  <note>Some print blurred.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2684:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Royall exchange: To ſuche worſhipfull Citezins / Marchants / Gentlemen and other occupiers of the contrey as reſorte therunto.</p>
            <p>Try to retaine / Or ſend back agayne.</p>
            <p>The contents ys after the Preface.</p>
            <p>Sene and allowed here.</p>
            <p>AT HARLEM. Printed wth Gylis Romaen. M.D.XCVII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2684:2"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2684:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2684:3"/>
            <head>To the worſhipful and grave Cittizin of London / Mr. A. T. wth others of my lovinge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quayntans in the Royall Exchange: grace and peace wyſhed to be compfortablie felt bothe in lyfe and at the inſtant of deathe / through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord accordinge to Moyſes / the Pſalmes and the Prophetts / Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eyther ſea particion nor diſtans of plaſe cann be anye lawfull excuſe to be ſo ſilent here / as abſent there / but rather the bonde of love conſidered / wth remembrans of your gentle favour / I dare no longer refrayne my penn / but as to ſum I wrote the laſt Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber / ſo thus printed to you and the reſt of my freynds this December. Whervnto as I am ſturred by dent of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian dutie / and the fullfillinge of the oulde proverbe: Better to late then never: ſo I truſt your approved curteſies wyl requite that ſayenge wth a nother as auncient: foone ynoughe yf well ynoughe. Knowinge that you accept aſwell the playne and wel meaninge as of eyther gloriouſe words / or eloquent wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge. Otherwiſe I conceyve not / how this ſmall valure to yours over valuynge / can eyther be ſoone ynoughe or well ynoughe. By whoſe acceptation / God grant bothe the many wryters / and the few readers of this age / no leſſ to abhor the ticklinge and erringe pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / the ytchinge eare / and flatteringe tounge for glori or gayne / then to be only gladd vnder aſſurans the ſearcher of thoughts dothe ſe ſo clerely the depthe and intent of harts: whether guyded by devyne grace or moved by corrupted nature. Wherfore ſeinge every good gyft as / preachinge writinge / edifying ſpeches / or the woreks of charptie procedinge from learned or vnlearned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes from the Lorde: I wyſhe ſuche good inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts poſſeſſing honeſt lyfe wth there rare gyfts / to reioyce and be gratefull for beinge the mowthe or hand of God / ſo mercifully chuſinge theme to be veſſells for his glorie / furtherouſe to his churche and profitable membres for the commune welthe. And greate reaſon they ſhould do ſo: ſeinge good teachers and famouſe writers on the one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2684:4"/>ſyde / labor to wynn Diſciples to Ieſus Chriſt / and not to theme ſelves / vndergoinge there greate paynes throw love and good conſcyens to beneficte many / and not for the expect of any vayne glorye. And on the other ſyde / the godly rytche to reioyce for that by the viſible word and inviſible grace they be taught to add St. Iames worcks wth St. Pauls faythe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cording theme to gethers by there words and practys as vnſeperable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions / in ſteade the greater forte by there cowld charitie and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reles lyves ſeme to rent theme a ſunder / the wch in dede ys more vnpoſſible then to devyde heate from the ſonne or ſhaddow from the bodie. For as the one iuſtifiethe before men here on yerthe / ſo dothe the other before Gods trybunall ſeate in heaven: the wch worcks of Gods children of what qualitie or qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie ſoever / are to be conſidered as the effects from the cauſe: whether the hand in gevinge / the toung in ſpeakyng / the pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n in writinge / or the hart in longinge to do more or better / all wch as obedyent daughters do wayte and attend in there degrees on there mother faythe / the very apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ieſus Chriſt God and man / and the hydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> roote gevinge ioyce and ſapp to the manifould bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the lords trees farr or nere / or whether more or leſſ / as the provident God hathe appoynted. And yet the leaſt portion of this faythe / dyſcearned by her effects ys ynouhe to attaine to the endleſſ crowne of glory. So graciouſe ys our God / in acceptinge the readines of willinge / where wantethe the habilitie of doinge. My worſipfull bretherne / you know there be many goodlye trees now a dayes in the wyde orchard of this worlde / eyther out / or but only in / and not of Chriſt his lyttle garden / who beare grene leaves and fayre bloſſomes / but alack eyther ſmale fruict or none at all / and that by a wronge vnderſtandinge of the compfortable article of iuſtification of faythe / preſuminge there by to be that they are not / to have that they want / and to obtayne that they ſhall not / vnleſt they do better reconſyle St. Paules faythe and St. Iames worcks to gether / wherby to reiect there ſauls hope for to be ſaved vp there naked and bare faythe / wch the Apoſtle compares to a deade corps wthout the ſpirit / more fytt for the low grave / then for the vpper grownd. But bleſſed ys that tree planted by the waterſyde of Gods ſpirit and word / wch bringeth for the her fructe in due ſeaſon. As though fruicts out of ſeaſon / be rather vnſavery / then pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſauery / as they are in dede / not only the worcks of our preſent Papiſts and Aunabaptiſts / the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2684:4"/>one wthout faythe / and the other as voyde of the true Chriſt: but ſuche perſons as be neyther of bothe: that is neglecters of the worde / abſenters from the Sermons / followers of there plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures / prorogers of charitable and compaſſionat duties vntill there death when they are de prived of the vſe of there goods. And yet I grant to ſum yt ys a ſeaſonable tyme by ſuche as were ſo exerciſed in there life / and wthout ſuperſtitiouſe meanyng at there deceaſe. Otherwiſe queſtion leff it ys out of ſeaſon. For now ys the tyme vnder lyfe to help one another by praper / cown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell / gevinge / or lendinge / but when ſoule or breathe ys gon / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther angells nor Apoſtles can geve any help or remidie. The poore may ſay to ſum ritche in theſe dayes / aſwell as in former tymes by funerall aulmes / gathamercy deathe: as the hoſtes rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konyng wth her geſt leſſ willinge to lodge in her hows / then his tyred horſe / made low curteſy in the mornynge to the beaſte / and ſeyde gathamercy horſe: foryf thow haddeſt not bene tyred / thy M<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. had not brought me this money. Luke as theſe proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of wel doinge having wherwth / are here iuſtly reproved / ſo the right vſers of Gods bleſſinghs in tyme oportune are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended / and God for there liberall hand to be prayſed and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified. Wherfore fyrſt let Stuards of larger portions make proufe to theme ſelves / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to others of there ſavinge faythe worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge by charitie and that in due tyme / whether yt be in gevinge therefully / or by lendinge to the godly poore in the pinche of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremetie / or by doore aulmes to the commune miſerable and hungerie / without this coulde and vſuall forewell: God help you. Next let men of meaner degre ſpare ſum exceſſ and vn neceſſarie expences for to follow the good example of there betters. And laſtly the meaneſt of all wantinge corporall habilitie / let theme lykewyſe approve there faythe to be moving and juſtifieng by the works of the ſpirit: as true love and zeale to Gods glorie / earneſt affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Gods worde and veritie / pitifull and mercifull harts / the thyrſt and hunger of well doinge / there hatred to heryſie and Hypocriſie / or by gevinge of ſownd and good cowncell: and by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge a religiouſe and vertuouſe converſation to the magnifieng of God and there holy profeſſion. Theſe alſo be acceptable worcks to the lorde / who in mercy will crowne theme as his owne gyfts and not as theres. The regard of wch promiſed crowne / ſette before the eyes of your mynds / will no leſſ mitigate your greifes eyther in ward or ontwarde / then kyndle ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2684:5"/>ioye / wth the longinge of your libertie from this ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtiall tabernacle / wherby your noble ſoules to enioy the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inheritans wth the inviſible and tryumphant churche now ſinginge as the Iſralitiſhe Virgins ſang the ſong of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for there delyverans out of Egipt and Pharo his bondage: evenſo the ſoules in Heaven do ſing to the Lord everlaſtinge prayſes for delyveringe them from the boude of ſathan and there worldlie miſeries: and lykewyſe do ſinge the ſonge of the Lambe wherby the vertue of Chriſt and his redemption ys continuallie magnified. For as the oulde fathers eatinge the paſchal Lambe made a iubilie and gave the Lord thancks: ſo thoſe enfranchiſed ſpirits / felinge the light and libertie of Gods kingdom / geve thancks to Chriſt the Lambe / to the ſytter on the throne / and to the ſpirit procedinge from bothe. Opraye for a fore taſie and ſum ſippinge of this greate ſupper where wth a farr of to be ſum what acquaynted / for the better certificate of a more fullnes to enſue / by wch to increaſe your earneſt longinge upwards and to decreaſe all overlyking here beneathe: that ſo the more felingly you may ſaye wth David / I ſhalve ſatiſffied when thy glorie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth / wch wilbe a greater ſight to behowld / then that wch Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Iohn ſaw at Chriſt his tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſfiguration on mowne Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor / even the fullnes of the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible dietie the eſſens of the gloriouſe perſons inſcrutablie one God. Let vs then be mynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſaye wth the Prophett / my ſoule ys a thirſt for God o when ſhall I appere before his preſons. Iff you Mr. A. do ſtill move and ſcur / love and lyve to the Lorde / then I moſie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie ſalute you / and the reſt ſo affected: but if otherwiſe / the ſpirit in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the bodie in the grave ere this be aryved: then God grant vs behynd in the battell to geve glory and thancks to hym for his contynuing grace and finall mercies here beneathe to his / and for his everlaſtinge compforthes a bove to the ſoules of his ſervants reſtinge wth hym in peace and iope. That ſo the Lorde havinge his ſpirit / I may the bowlder to that coniecture ſet that oulde father as a glaſſ for Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don profeſſors to looke in: not alone in his zeale to the goſpell / wth his frequent preſens at Sermons / and wth good further ans to ſuche inſtruments / but to the poore preſoners in and abowt London preſons he was knowen to be bowntiful and mercifull. Agayne how ofte and willingly hathe be Imployed his money for commune profict as well as for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat? what paynes and travell hathe he take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make peace and to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2684:5"/>end controverſies? how many men of worſhip and members of the lower hows in moſt parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tymes haue bene worſhipfullie entertayned at his table for there zeale to religion? how many poore ſchollers and ſtudents in the arts hath he no leſſ perely the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberally geven vnto? beſydes his large diſtributions to Godly and deſolate widdowes. And wch ys more / how manie in the contrey of worr are bownd to prayſe God for his outſtretched hand ſo farr from London? wherein he procured the knowlege of God for greate ignorans: beinge ſuche a ſhew toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to patrons of benefices / as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he franckly gave ſo good a lyvinge to a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned preacher / he reſerved neither legg nor arme of that lyvinge to hym ſelf / as all covetous patrons do. God grant yt be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly perfourmed by labor and life as it was of hym firſt and laſt intended. For as gyfts blynde the eyes of ſum Iudges: ſo fatt lyvings coole the fyrſt zeale of manie perſons and vicars. For inward alterations do ofte follow the ſtayne of ſtrange ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles. Now whether this was a tree bringing forthe fructe in due ſeaſon or out of ſeaſon / iudge you beſydes the erection of a ſchole as I remember in worr. And there fore as St. Paul would hym ſelf to be imitated non otherwiſe then he did Chriſt: even ſo I wiſhe the Lords Stewards of better degre in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change / to follow this theire fellow me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ver as he followed Chriſt and the worthier examples of his predeceſſors. Truſtinge you will thinck this report to procede more for deſire of imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / then of anie intent to tyckle hym wth adulation / being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure gon or at leaſt of ſuche diſtans a ſunder. To conclude / bothe hearing and ſeinge ſuche evident practys of good worcks in this towne of Harlem ſo farr ſhort of our monarchall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by ſownde profeſſors and others of erroniouſe opinious: I was drive<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rather to this preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as one ſory to behoulde ſuche blynd opiniates ſo farr to outrun very many profeſſors in my natyve contrey in the outward worcks of charitie and by hearinge that the ignorants are ſo affected vnto theme for yt / wher by the rather there might be a quycknyng wth a godly emulation on our ſyde / ere the axe come to the roote of the tree. <hi>1597.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your worſhips vnfayned wellwyller Iohn Payne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2684:6"/>
            <head>The contents of the Booke fyrſt the preface for all as for one.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Next to ſeverall degrees of perſons.</item>
               <item>Aldermen.</item>
               <item>Marchants of three ſortes.</item>
               <item>Stranger Marchants.</item>
               <item>Saduceans of this age.</item>
               <item>Gentlemen three ſortes.</item>
               <item>Warnyng to avoyde new Englyſche Anabaptiſts.</item>
               <item>There ſeven opinions and fauls martyrdome.</item>
               <item>An exhortation to theme.</item>
               <item>Tyme to be well ſpent and why.</item>
               <item>Hypocrites of ſundry ſortes.</item>
               <item>Groſſ pryde / wth the dreggs therof in Gods children.</item>
               <item>Poore of two ſortes.</item>
               <item>Prynters of two ſortes.</item>
               <item>Shipinayſters and maryners.</item>
               <item>Mariage corporall and ſpirituall.</item>
               <item>How Chriſt is Godman and mangod.</item>
               <item>Captaynes and ſouldyers.</item>
               <item>To the Englyſhe Anabaptiſt in norwith Preſon.</item>
               <item>Warrs ys lawfull and why.</item>
               <item>Spirituall warrs.</item>
               <item>Muſers on Gods longanimitie and providens.</item>
               <item>Miniſters of England exhorted.</item>
               <item>Curiouſe medlers wth impertinent matters.</item>
               <item>A deceyver in the exchange.</item>
               <item>The Nordeners exhorted.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2684:6"/>
            <head>Now Gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Yke as the greate reſorte to that famouſe Edifice / are of ſundrie titles and degrees: ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete nomber walkinge and taulkinge there be as contrarie in mynd and diſpoſition / as of trade and caullinge / A plaſe where God / truth and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / wth there direct contraries are ſum tymes ſpoken of to Gods glorie / and to the ſervice of Sathan. For as amonge diſeaſed and infectiouſe perſons / all be not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wth that ſicknes / but ſum do eſcape and be ſcottfre: ſo I partly know the lyke fredome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall infection by Gods mercie in ſum members of that popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe aſſemblie. The Lord multiply that nomber / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d increaſe his bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n graces in theme / and alſo convert or confownde all perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe lurckers preaſinge thether ſo contrarie mynded. As you take tyme and ſpace to make your lawful bargaines a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracts: ſo haue you now a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then convenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t leyſure to talke and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferr be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene thoſe pillers of the omnipotent a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d allſeinge God / of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and good lyfe ſo neceſſarie at all ſeaſons / but in eſpecial now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſweerde of Gods iuſtis ſemes to be ſhaken over you there / aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as vs here / threatnyng direfull warrs famyne confuſion of good order and ſtrange ſyckneſſes: by wch the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſuffering God will haue his hand to be ſelt / when his gentle voyce cannot be hearde / wherby bothe prowd and diſſolute fleſh to ſtowpe and to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in dreade of hym ſo wilfully refuſinge to ſerve a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d obey hym. The ſcreptures geves no libertie / nor exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptethe perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor plaſe to be ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Goda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his glorie / moche leſſ to be prophanly occupied: but rather byndethe ſum devine exerciſe in convenient meaſure every where. As whether you eate or drinck / or what ſoever you do / etc. Lykewiſe in all tymes and places: the texts you know wel ynouge for knowlege is rife / the lord grant grace and vertu therwth to habownde.</p>
            <p>To come now to perticulers:<note place="margin">Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> and firſt to begyn wth the right worſhipfull Aldermen of the citie / repayringe thether wth there fellow bretherne / aſwell on cittie cauſes / as for there private. To the wch the bleſſinge of compforthe and happie ſucceff ys due / if God to thoſe ends be firſt craved / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his deſerved glory advanced by reyellinge of inturiouſe ſutes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge the poore innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2684:7"/>Then are they two fowld rytche and happie / wthin and wthout and moſt worthy of dowble honor / as ys required of the elders of the churche that lyve and governe well. But no more of that / whoſe grave and worſhipfull perſons / as they do no leſſ dignifie that plaſe and greate companie / then dutifullie procure the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens of all / evenſo they addinge there religiouſe affections / wth there fatherly indevers to better there well doyngs in due ſeaſon / yt ſhall wynn general love and lovinge harts / beſydes Gods perpetuall bleſſinge and favoure / and when they are gon / as generall prayſes to hym for there Iuſtis pietie / and equitie / and for there redreſſ of that wch ys contrarie. The wch ys farr more of valure then all gyfts and bequeſts they leave behynde theme: Salomon ſayeth better ys a good name then moche rytches / the wch St. Paul eſtemeth as dunge in reſpect to wynn Ieſus Chriſt / whyle he ys to bewonne / that ys to daye / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he willeth to do good while time ys. For if there predeceſſors in the dayes of ſuche ignorans were ſo diligent to draw credit to there popiſhe maſſ a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d idolatrouſe traſhe? how moche more wth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon ought thoſe worſhipfull elders beget love and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite in this brightnes of the goſpel / firſt to Gods truthe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by theme / and next to there caullings and perſons. And ſeing the remembrans of deathe / dothe moche further the reforminge of lyfe: I wyſhe bothe the exchange / cytie and contrey / to think of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on the wadde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> horſe or foure foted bere / ſo ſodaynly comminge from other mens doores to theires / wthout gevinge of fore knowlege / and to carie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a waye for ever and ever / on four me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhoulders / from there warme and lightſome habitations / to the cowld and clapeſhe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions / and from there pleaſant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie of wife childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and familie / to the fellowſhip of gredie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d crawlinge wormes inobſcuritie / next to bethinck on the wayters and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on there immortall ſoules at the departure from there car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall coffyns / to a better or worce place / beinge either the angells of light or the miniſters of darckenes / as yt fell out on Lazarus a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d dives / to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducte theme to incogitable pleaſure / or to tearmleſſ terror. The remembrans of this tragedie / will verylie inſtructe the faythful reader to watche and praye / to be oft ner at fructeful Sermons / wth purpoſe of practis / to abate pryde and ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / to beſtow the more where there ys neceſſitie / to be as warie of the world / as of a familier traytor / breifly to regard better the worcks of mercie in due ſeaſon / ſeinge yt is written iudgement wthout mercie ſhal be to theme that will ſhew no mercie. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2684:7"/>here I wyſhe you banniſhe from your tables ſuche Atheiſts and machivells as be the Devills ſcicophants and trencher ſlaves to make men laughe at there tuſhinge and ſcoffinge of religiouſe matters / beinge ſo emptie of the grace of wepinge for there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable ſynnes. Wherfore as your worſhipfull tables be for a better companie: ſo let your doores and portalls in lyfe tyme / and not the churche porche after death be your almeries / and ſede grownd for the increaſe of yerthly and celeſtiall fructe / and let your gates be knowen the place where you lend to the lord / that truſtie pay maiſter and moſte higheſt threaſurer / who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payeth more then tenn thowſand for the hundred: and vouchſafe to loke to the poore howſhould of faythe in a nother place and after a better ſorte / for that they be a ſhamed in there nede to come to your doores or to begg in the ſtrete: whoſe prayers and prayſes is more odoriferouſe and acceptable before the lorde / then all ſumpteouſe funeralls how gloriouſe ſoever coveringe rotten bones and wthout any avayle to there departed ſoules. Neyther condembninge here nor prevelie checkinge worſhipfull and ſeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order then / accordinge to the degrees of perſons / but the exceſſ and waſtefull ſpendinge of Gods creatures / bothe in lyfe and deathe: the wch beinge not yours abſolutely to beſtow theme as you liſt / but the lords (and that lent you his conſtituted bayliffes for your ſelves and others) you ſhall ſurely anſwere and make accowmpte for the laveſſ and mſſpendinge of your mayſters goods: as the vnrighteouſe Stuard was put out of office for the ſame faulte. This abuſe amended vp the vertu of Gods grace herevnto a nexed / then by your workinge faythe ye provide after deathe to haue an heavenly habitacion / as that worldly wyſe Stuard providid for an earthly / when he ſhould be caſt out: for the wch providens to inſtruct others: the lord commended hym accordinge to the maner of men / and not his vnrighteouſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge. Thus doinge / you prove religiouſe / and profeſſ religion for religion ſake / and not for ſum other thinge / as ſum perſons do the miniſterie more for the lyvinge ſake / them for Gods glorie: then are you right Royall exchangers / changed from an ould into a new nature / and from followinge your owne wylls to obeye the wyll of the lord your God. And for the ſpedier practys of ſuche deſyred duties / I wyſhe the preachers in cyttie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to forbeare for a tyme St. Paul his ſwete doctrine of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of faythe / and a nother while to take in hande S. Iames
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2684:8"/>and his iuſtification of worcks ſo rarely ſeene: who never the leſſ aſmoche confirmethe his fellow Apoſtles doctrine in that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly article (proper to the greved and humbled ſoule) as he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifiethe the preſumpteouſe and careles liver / whoſe fayth he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to the faythe of tremblinge devills / as appereth by there deſtitution of zeale to Gods glorie / or brotherly love and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion / and yet thinck theme ſtlves Chriſtians good ynoughe for there preſens in the congregations / for there thruſtinge to the communion / or for there bare taulke of the ſcriptures. God bleſſ vs from ſuche an hypocriticall faythe. The poſſeſſors wher of ſtand in more nede of the terror of the law / as fyrſt a hammer to beate theme downe / then of de gentle voyce and hand of the goſpell to lyft theme vp.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cumpanie be marchant venturers / and marchant retaylers / who moſt rightly beare the name of changers in that reputable exchange / changinge wares for money / and money for wares.<note place="margin">Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</note> And therfore our ſoueraigne Ladie in aboliſhing the fyrſt title (Buſſ) and impoſinge a new / as ther by ſhe had prudent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to tearme yt the exchange accordinge to the nature of that marchantlike trade: ſo in greate favour ſhe bare to it and the whole Cittie / ſhe added thereto a regall title / and then tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it the Royall exchange. God preſerve and bleſſ her Princely hart wth his grace and ſpirit / for the further and more ample advancement of his glorie / bothe in England / and her wonted helpe for other troubled contreys a bowt her. And the lord cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge there harts / or cutt of ther bodies from the yerthe that wyſhe or practys the contrarie / to the pleaſinge of Gogg the Pope / and his Catholike kinge wth his ſpaniſhe mynes the horne of his ſtrengthe. Now that your traffyke ys hyndered / navigation reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayned / and your former gaynes greatly Impayred: I wyſhe you fyrſt to acknowlege the finger of God in all this for ſynn: and next to wey and conſider of the ſpirituall marchantdiſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned of in the goſpell / wth the hydden threaſure not fownd wthout paynfull digginge / and of the good marchant buyeng the preciouſe pearle / Implieng therby that devine rytches cannot be obtayned wthout zeale and earneſt affection / wthout ſearche and diligent ſekinge / and vnleſt they be redemed wth the beſt things you affect / and to eſteme all other marchantdiſe but tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles whether from Turckie or Denice in compariſon of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine threaſure. And marck that no adventurers nor the ſecure or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2684:8"/>careleſſ can fynd the ſayde hydden threaſure. The Kyngdom of God muſt be ſought ere yt can befownde: therfore let the name marchant teacht all to make ſinguler accowmpt of ſpirituall and ſacred things and of the goſpell / Sacraments / readinge hearing / prayeng / Pſalmes and ſongs from the hart. O that we could love and regarde theſe preciouſe pearles / the ſupernaturall threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hyd from the worldly hart / and the goſpell of Chriſt as they are to be eſtemed / wch ys the gladdeſt news and ioyfulleſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings / the light of the churche and every ſoule therof / the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative of the Prince / and the pyller of her Kyngdom: the wch beinge taken a way / deſpiſed or lothed / as manna was of the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge Iſcalites yt muſt nedes fall out wth vs as it did on that full gorged people / when the ark of God was taken from theme: namely bloddie warrs / hunger / famine / peſtilences / and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions before and behynde. Iff you dyd but ſum tymes wey and conſider this: then would you be as deſirouſe of the continuans of the goſpell by due eſtimation of ſuehe a threaſure for to ſave and defend you from Gods wrathe / as the elders of Iſraell co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the lords ark (the figure therof) to ſave theme from the Philiſtines / who in there miſerie crped out / ſayeng / wherfore hathe the lord ſmitten vs? let vs bringe againe the ark of Gods covenant a mongeſt vs / that when it commeth it may ſave vs from the hands of our enemies. And then as dagon could not ſtand / but fall downe and breake his neck at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens of Gods arck: ſo can neyther the ſecond ſpaniſhe flete / the power of papiſts / wth the indian gould be able to ſtand / but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flee and conſume from the Quene of England and her reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſe ſubiects / when they put this Evangelicall arck in revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and hartie maner betwene theme and there adverſaries: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then the wch love and reverens / yt wilbe as meake a buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler at the fierce aſſaulte as the arck of God was to the Iſralites when they / there Kinge and preiſt were all over chrowen. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly remember that you muſt be changed you know not when / from your ritches / from this vitall lijfe and the whole worlde vnto a nother place paynefull or Ioyfull / none otherwiſe then the ſayde preciouſe pearle and hydd threaſure is of price and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure wth you for the preſent tyme. Thinck of this / and on hym that exhortethe to be changed and renewed in the inward man / carefully ſtudienge to change the owld life for a new / even as you tender the changinge of this mortalitie / to Immortalitie / of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2684:9"/>drudgerie beneathe to the felicitie above: ſeing yt is written that ſuche as ſhalbe burgeſes there / they muſt be ſo enfranchiſed here / as to be made Kings and preiſts to overcom and to offer / no leſſ then Prophetts to inſtruct theme ſelves and there familie / and al to ſhew forthe the vertues of hym that hathe caulled theme out of darckues into his marvelouſe light.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Evill Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</note>And further vnderſtand / that as there be honeſt and Godlie men of your trade: ſo the very contrarie are bothe knowen and felt / who yet marche vnder the enſigne of honeſt marchants / and would appere as religiouſe as they be covetouſe or impiouſe: beinge as greate a ſcandale to that worſhipfull companie / as corrupt lyvers and teachers do greyve the Godlie learned in the miniſterie. Theſe marchants deceyve moche by there paynted faulſhode and lipp religion / wherby they endamage others to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritche there eſtate. Suche ys the choyce that theſe make of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie and hypocriſie / when they affect ſo little the grace of truthe and ſimplicitie. Theſe fellows wyll brave yt out / how ſlender ſo ever they be wthin / and preaſe to be eyther equall or higher then there betters / fleinge the meane eſtate wch is the happieſt / and ſteale credit by other mens valure / vntill they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come eyther breakers or banckerers. God in mercie geve ſuche repentans for borrowinge and dealinge wth many / and to kepe towche wth few. Exceptinge here nevertheles ſuche honeſt men as come to decaye / neyther by the pryde of there backs / wyfe / nor table / but by ſhipwrack on the ſea / or by truſtinge the vntruſtie that borrow moche / and repay eyther little or nothinge. But God that never chaſtiſeth wthout cauſe dyd ſe yt tyme to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect / for eyther beinge over gredie to aſpire / or by covetouſe deſyre of exceſſive gaynes / dyd rather chuſe to write there bad creditors names in there bookes / then to take preſent pay in there purſes of honeſt cuſtomers: or otherwyſe / the Lord ſaw cowldnes and backwardnes in religion / by nuſzlinge to depely in the world / wherby at lengthe to borrow of three and ſcarce to paye one. Seinge then that God ſo ſharplie correcteth ſuche profeſſors as by toyles and cares retire from there religiouſe affections: yt ys good to pray for a contented mynde / to norriſhe your firſt love and zeale to God by all due meanes / and not to ſuffer the world / and deſyre of equalitie wth others to quenche the ſame: and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of puttinge on the gay cloke of religion / for any other cauſe then for religion yt ſelf / wch rightly poſſeſſed makes the differens
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2684:9"/>betwene brute beaſts and men or / rather betwene devills and ſaincts. And to invite preachers to your table / more to learne of theme and to be reproved by theme / nede ſo requiringe then to gett any fame or glorie thereby. And foraſmoche as marchants can hardly kepe theme ſelves from wronge (ſpun ſticking ſo faſt to that trade as nayle in the wall) they muſt bothe pray the more earneſtly / and ſay wth Job / I did feare all my worcks: and not to forgett that you be ſubiect to change and caſualties: and next to be thankfull for your daylie gettings / leſt otherwiſe in a tyme vnloked for / you crie wth the rytch marchants of babilon: alaſſ alaſſ for in one hower ſo greate ritches ys come to deſolation. The anabaptiſts do well in commendinge manuell trades / and we confeſſ it worthie of commendacion / becauſe yt ys furtheſt of from defylinge pitche: but they fowlie err in denyenge marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe to be Gods ordinans / ſeinge buyenge and ſellinge is one of the leggs / whervpon every common welthe dothe ſtand / for the better helpe of Prynce / nobles and contrey / otherwyſe Abraham / Iacob and the reſt would not buy there lauds to bury in / nor the ſale of land in booze his tyme. Only the Lord requireth equitie / right dealinge and ells what / wch ys more commonly knowen / then practyſed.</p>
            <p>The thrid ſort be retaylers in the vpper ſhopps: In wch place as there be honeſt men and auncient matrons that occupie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall and profitable wares / to the beneficte of the buyers:<note place="margin">Retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</note> ſo ys yt otherwyſe of the reſt reported. But becauſe men love better gentle admonitions / then bytter vmbradings: therfore I wyſhe bothe yong men and reputed virgins there to wynn credit to the hows and to theme ſelves / by deſert of better fame then is abrode / and to be no leſſ honeſt and chaſte yong men / ſober damſelles and virgins in dede and in proufe / then they are in face and ſhew / for to ſtopp the mowthes of ſuche yll reporters: eſchewinge levitie and wantonnes / wth the pride of hart / gate / and apparell / and not to ſitt ydlie and gaſinge about / but eyther havinge leyſure to be profitablie readinge / or as the Apoſtle ſayethe to labor and worck ſum good thing wth there handes for there owne behoufe and others. By wch yt apperethe that the holy Goſt allowethe not the makinge and ſellinge of badd and deceytefull things / nedeles toyes for the increaſe of greater pryde / leſt God be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. To conclude God keye you from the contempt of this ſhort and freyndly admonition / and grant you his holy feare / the love
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2684:10"/>of true Godlynes / and the hatred of all wyckednes / wth carefull watche for the ſoveraigne Iudge ſo haſtelie comminge to Iudge bothe quich and deade.</p>
            <p>Fourthly the frenche and dutche marchants walkinge in that Royall place.<note place="margin">Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> Moſte of you be in the churche / and I hope of the churche / thoughe ſum tymes the wolfe be wthin the fowld / when the ſhepe ys wthout. Many of your companie my ſelf dothe know to be of as good diſpoſition / as of a ſownd profeſſion / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payringe fyrſt to our contrey from the rage of the enemie for the zeale you bare to Gods religion. Wherfore as your churches be entituled reformed / ſo (accordinge as you be gravely inſtructed) indever moche to refourme your lyves and maners / your dedes and actions / bothe huſbands and wyves / after the doctryne and order of a reformed church / wherby to draw credite and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thoſe large aſſemblies for / the honor of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel / and to avoyde the gevinge of offens to the ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the ſame / and the dſcredit of the churches in London and ells where: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this careful watch / looke for nothing but a more heavie iudgement to light on your heades / then on theme that want the good meane you have. And as for ſuche ſtrangers as be wthout the zeale of Gods honor and the care to lyve vertuouſely / ſuche as be vnſaciable rakers of rytches / hynderers of the poore / and ſervers of there belly more then of God / the Lord purge the churche of ſuche Hypocrites yf any of thoſe be amongeſt you. And the others that have as little vnion or communion wth you / but be eyther papiſts / anabaptiſts or open atheiſts God change theme from cittie and contrey. Wyſhinge bothe prentices / and other youthes of the Cittie bearinge grudge and yll will to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſe ſtrangers to purge there harts of all former malys and to favour theme whome bothe God and Prince dothe expreſſly ſo commande: as Levit <hi>19.</hi> Yf A ſtranger dwell with you in your land you ſhall not vex hym / but he ſhall be as one of your ſoules / and thow ſhalt lobe hyn as thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>Fyfthlie ſum new Saduces and libertynes / now and then do trepe and walke in the middeſt of you:<note place="margin">Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans.</note> as Iob ſayeth / that ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commes a monge Gods children. The wch deade ſoule parſons vnder vitall lyfe / proclaymes warninge for all that woulde lyve wth Chriſt Ieſus to avoyde there fearefull eſtate and dambnable opinions / no leſſ then ovr bodies do ſhunn the poyſon of ſpiders. And ſeinge the Lorde hathe given over ſuche vnbelevers of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2684:10"/>generall reſurrection to the power of ſathan / exceptinge the ſaide vitall lyfe reſerved longer for a fuller meaſure of there extreme iniquitie / wherby to be chayned in there hellyſhe inheritans: I wiſhe and exhorte every worſhipper of God poſſeſſinge the hope of our ioyfull ryſinge agayne / bothe to pray and to reade moche for to be rooted in a preſent and lyvely felinge of a greater confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of that gladſome reſurrection: bothe to mitigate all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greyfes / and the better to ſeale Gods eternall election wthin there harts. And no leſſ to beware of there copartners and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geringe diſciples / neyther wholie wth theme nor flattly againſt theme / but waveringe betwene bothe / becauſe the ladder of there rude reaſon / ys not long ynoughe to reache to ſuche an highe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie: lyke the anabaptiſts denienge the humanitie of Chriſt to come from his mother / becauſe there ſhallow reaſon can not reache how then he cowld be wthout ſynn. Therfore as the one reiectethe the true Chriſt / profeſſinge another wth his fleſh from ells where: ſo our new Saduces blott out from there harts all maner of thought of that moſte terrible and ioyfull day of the Lorde: ſtudienge for no more then to eate drynck and be mery / vntill to morrow they dye as the brute oxe / thoughe not ſo well. To the wch myſchefe they are come by voluptuouſe ſecuritie / wth the neglect or contempt of Gods worde / and ſo be inſnared wth darch and deadly dowtes in this light of the goſpell. Theſe ſtaggerers wth there grand Captaynes do call Gods provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and his regiment over all into queſtion / aswell as the ryſinge of our bodies: as thus / how can there be an outſtretched providens from God above to vs here beneathe / ſeinge there ys ſuche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions and diſtractions in the world / ſo manyfould hurly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies / and vnſpeakable iniuries by one man to another wthout redreſſ: the worce diſpoſed doinge all outrage / in A floriſhinge and pleaſant eſtate: and ſuche as be eſtemed Godly / to be moſt miſerable / oppreſſed / vexed and ſett nought by: all wch ſhould not be if there were any ſuche provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For brevitie ſake I muſt ſilence the anſwere: who might aswell ſay / how cowld there be of God / and his providens in former tymes ſeinge not only Abel and Iohn the Baptiſt Gods ſpeciall ſervants were ſo ſharply rewarded for there holynes and righteouſenes / but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetts Apoſtles and Chriſt hym ſelf. All this were as moche as if the preſidents and ſo many thowſand martyrs were ſtarck fooles to ſuffer ſuche torments and tortures / vnleſt they had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2684:11"/>knowlege of Gods providens wth a right felinge and hope of the laſt reſurrection: wthout wch / the vildeſt men in the world were in the libertie of the fleſhe in farr better ſtate then we. Theſe new Saduces wth there ſtaggeringe diſciples / ſeke to comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by there pudled reaſon / that wch is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehencible to humayne wiſdom: and do marvell how the bodies ſo long tyme putrified in the grownd / mangled by ſwerds and weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / burnt to aſhes / torne and eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wilde beaſts a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d devowred of ſea fiſches / how a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d after what maner all theſe ſhould riſe by againe / wth the ſame bodies and bodilie members. Who he lyke the vnbelevinge Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynthes tearmed fooles by the Apoſtle and therfore diſputed wth only by the ſimilitude of corne and naturall reaſon. Theſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king queſtioners / labor to throw downe faythe beneathe reaſon: and to attayne by reaſon / that wch is proper to the office of faythe. To whome ſo ever the wch faythe ys not geven vnder ſo longe tyme of the goſpell yt is no marvell they dowte and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger / and become rather curiouſe inquiſiters / then Godlie lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: and ſo might demande how the lorde cowld make Adam of claye / and Eve of his ribb: or how they thre parſons ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n be one God / and one to be three? ſo daringe to meddle wth the miſtery of all miſteries / lyke the Anabaptiſts / no leſſ quiſitive in effect / to wete how cowld the Devinitie of Chriſt aſſume his fleſhe of hers that was ſo ſtayned by originall gilt. Let the Royall Exchange / Cittie and contrey beware of theſe perilouſe people / avoydinge there dowtes and devilliſhe queſtions: exhortinge there wth that they be frequent hearers and readers of Gods holie worde / for to be daylie ſtrengthned in there faythe and hope wth better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the articles of the Chriſtian faythe: eſpeciallie two of theme ſo moche oppugned by multiplienge adverſaries bothe here and there: namely the anabaptiſts Engliſhe and dutche / denyeng the two natures of Chriſt in one gloriouſe parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wth <hi>6.</hi> more horrible opinions: and the ſayde dowters of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now let all right belebers in the true Chriſt from Mop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / the Pſalmes and de Prophetts / reioyce and be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth vnder what croſſ or diſtreſſ ſoever: For aſſure as he hathe taken our fleſhe / ſanctifienge and glorifiengc yt: ſo ſurely ſhall we be glorified wth hym / ſeing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he our heade the fyrſt fructs of theme that ſlept ys riſen agayne / aſſended wth our ſubſtans the ſede of David and hathe dignifyed yt on the right hand of his father / as he toke yt and ſanctified yt here beneathe. As cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2684:11"/>ſhall we his members fleſh and boane of his ryſe agayne to be partakers of his Ioyes as we have bene partakers of his bleſſings here and ſuffrnigs. That yf the huſbandman hopeth the corne ſowen by his hand vnder clodds and ſtones ſhall riſe againe / new / freſh / and wth greate in creaſe: moche more ought we to hope that our bodies ſhall riſe againe by Gods omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie as ſede ſowen wth his owne hand whether in the grave in the fyer / in theſe a / or in the feilde renewed and clarified with vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keable increaſings / and that wth no more difficultie then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he made the whole frame of this world without ſubſtans or matter by his very worde. St. Paul would vs to remember / that as the corne muſt fyrſt be ſowen and dye in the yerthe before yt receyve a new bodye / a grene blade and ripe eare: ſo muſt we be the lords ſedenes before the happie harveſt / namely / ſowen / deade / buried / and rotten / before we have a gloriouſe and Immortall bodie / even the ſame in ſubſtants / thoughe in qualitie yt ſhalbe changed / and then to be caulled ſpirituall bodies / differinge in ſuche ſorte from that they were before / as the celeſtiall bodies / the ſonn moone and ſtarrs do differ one from another in glorie. At wch tyme our harts / eyes and eares ſhal feele ſe and heare ſuche a marveylouſe thang of the vſe they were here / as neyther toungs nor all the pennes in the world are able to Expreſſ. And therfore happie be the penitents for there ſynnes / the ſtudiers for God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines / and the lovers of God: and bleſſed are they that in faithe do meditate / and in hope do reioyce ſum tymes on this Ioyfull daye. Concludinge then that as there ys two deathes the fyrſt and ſecond / in yerth and in hell: ſo there vs a fyrſt and ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection / that ys from ſynne and from the grave / the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of the one / ys the confirmation of the other: And when our ſoules do inviſiblie go from the bodies: then that ſpirituall and Immortall part goethe vnto the heaven of heavens and not downe to the grave to ſlepe there wth the corps vntyll the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection / as oure anabaptiſts of Harlem / and the reſt do miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie howld wth the purtenances.</p>
            <p>Sixtly the worſhipfull Gentlemen of all quarters of the land are by occaſion ſum tymes wthin that pleaſant Edifice wth whome I muſt be breyffer then I thought to have bene.<note place="margin">Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> Preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge lykewyſe that they in curteſie wyll eſteme of this poore pamphlett / thoughe wthout fynenes of methode / or pulliſhe of art. You then of the better ſorte tearmed gentle / as gentlemen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2684:12"/>deryved from gentle condiſions: remember I pray you that as by the word of healthe you once felt / and I truſt do yet feele / ſpirituall motions the very inward caullinge from the Lorde to the love and zeale of his truthe: ſo to geve all diligens that you be no changelings / but dutifully the ſame / what cownterbuffs ſo ever do come in your way to the contrarie. Affectinge the good and diſlikinge the evell. And let your fortitude be in ſylens and hope / wth prayer and paciens: thoughe ſum paradventure on eache ſyde of your habitacions do eyther hault / or be key could or gonn back from that they were wth you / or as ſtarrs faullen / there light vnder a buſhell / other ſum choked wth the world / and ſum of a looſer lyfe then ever you looked for: yet as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias continued the ſervant of God thoughe he ſaw none to be left wth hym but all gonn: and Iob the worthy ſervant of God in ſo evill a tyme wherin moche vngodlynes was in the world / yet ſtode he faſt in his goode lyfe / thoughe he ſaw few ſo affected / to gether wth righteouſe Lott nothing returned from his holy converſation notwthſtanding the multitude of wycked Sodomites on every ſide: but the one and the other proceded and parſiſted in there pietie: In lyke ſorte ſtand you faſt / quite you lyke men / procede as ſpirituall ſouldiers / and ſo to finiſhe as true Chriſtians / and then the garland to come ys yours / wth the preſent peace of conſciens / wch in this lyfe vs the cheyfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of true Godlynes. The other part of gentlemen ſo naked of the weddinge garment / as they be voyde of oyle in there lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / lovinge better to follow the crye of there hownds / then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to heare the voyce of the preacher / or to imitate your Godly example: I wyſhe vs all to pittie and pray for theme / that make ſo ſmall accowmpt of religion and good lyfe / otherwyſe then of there belly God and ladie pleaſure: who therby / as they ſeme to be flatt Atheyſts and therefore in moſt wofull caſe: ſo the papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call gentlemen (as fauls harted to goſpell and Prynce as they be addicted to romiſhe Idolls) be as vnfitt for civill office and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie / as by want of faythe they are yet for the Kingdom of glorie: whervnto the Lord frame and convert theme / in the tyme of his yourpoſe and pleaſure. But you good gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt think on the dignitie of your profeſſion / of the ſervant knowing moch to do his mayſters will / on the brevitie of your dayes / of the beſt exerciſes to be had therein / and in tyme of your recreations to glorifie God / and to beware of prophanations / takinge greate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2684:12"/>delight in your graciouſe God / not alone for your welthe health / leyſure and libertie / but cheyfly for his illumininge ſpirit / the feare of the Lorde / and for that by grace you diſcearne your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to ſtand the contreyes in ſteade / and your good examples to be as glaſſes for theme to looke in. Then may that circuit be cownted happie conteyninge ſo vertuouſe an examplar / as the congregation moſt bleſſed to have before theme a Godly and learned teacher. Therfore for the better approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ſtate and degrees / to be a warrantable caullings from God (ſo mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telie denyed of ſum) fyrſt as you are curteouſe and gentle vp the guyde of your names / ſo in other things to be fownde wthin rule and good order: ofte wthin the lords hows / as a ſure recorde you be of the ſame / lyvinge ſtones and helpinge members lovers of the Prynce / proctors for her good cauſes / but more ſpecially for Gods / and that in good ſort wth whome you muſt lyve beyond the tyme of all Prynces: helpinge gentlemen / but not hurtinge neyghbors of the poore in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys. Lykewiſe you worſhipful of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yne acquayntans both diſcrete and of good carriage of your ſelues / I pray you preferr the holynes of religion by being found truly religiouſe / that ſo your fellowe gentlemen may be aſhamed to ſpeake evill of your good profeſſion / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhall ſe you hate vice / love vertu / releyve the poore / to bringe vp your familie in the knowlege and reverens of God / as I have knowen you to have donn ſum in the cittie and more in the contrey: of wch nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there be to few / and theme over baſely eſtemed though of great price before the Lorde and his people redemed. In the meane tyme my worſhipfull freynds I humblie crave the helpe of your prayers in this farr diſtans occaſioned partly by ſum doctorly frownes partly by my daughters letters and by greate boaſts to ſe ſuche en Engliſhe churche here as nompareille and ſo yt ys par derrriere and finally throughe raſhe truſt in ſum not ſo truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / wherby the oulde man was hether tranſported / to be of his God iuſtly and gently corrected.</p>
            <p>And further to premoniſhe bothe you and the worſhipfull in the exchange: I wijſhe you beware of the dangerouſe opinions of ſuche Englyſhe Anabaptiſts bred here / as whoſe parſons in part wth more ſtore of there letters dothe creps and ſpreade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt you in cittie and contrey. The wch perilouſe heryſies wherewth they be ſo lately infected / dyd not only procede of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie in error / but of pryde and ſingularitie / wth the want of love and humilitie to kepe vnitie and peace amonge theme ſelves
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2684:13"/>when they came over. And as by my privat letters I have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned ſum particuler frepuds: ſo by this ſymple and forrayne labor / I intended a more generall: ſithens I heard that one of this companie in Norwich intendeth to indure ſhortly an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt hym. By wch premoniſhement I would gladly make you more carefull and watchefull to prevent the inviſible ſower of darnell a monge the good wheate. And ſo no leff to ſeke the right armure of prouffe and ſhilde of defens for our devine cauſes / wherby to foyle theme that intend to defyle others then they ſeke fauls armure by wreſt of ſcripture / wth wyle wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to make vnlawfull reſiſtans againſt the moſt holy and auncient fayth of the vniuerſall churche / the wch not to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne and defend in ſum meaſure by the O Chriſtian / reader and every true member of the ſame / were ſuche &amp; threaſon to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke faythe / and to her obiect Ieſus Chriſt / as the Turcks / Iews / and Papiſts ſhould be farr better then theye bp reaſon in there blynde zeale they ſtudie and labor all they can to ſupport there fauls religions / and to gayneſay the contrarie. And dareſt thow of what condiſion ſo ever tuſhe and make light of this as thoughe yt appartayned not to the? God forbid.</p>
            <div type="warning">
               <head>Gentlemen warned of the opinions of the Anabaptiſts.</head>
               <p>Fyrſt our Engliſhe and Outche here howld that Chriſt toke not his pure fleſhe of the Virgin Mary: and do denie her to be his naturall mother. Secondly that the Godheade was ſubiect to paſſions and to deathe wch ys Impaſſible. Thyrdly that the infants of the faythfull ought not to be baptyſed. Fourthly that the ſoules do ſlepe in grave wth the bodies vntill the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fyfthly that Maicſtrates ought not to put malefactors to deathe. Sixtly they condemne all warrs and Subiects in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure in the feyld. Seventhly they denyt the article of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they denye the L. day. And finally they ſavour moch of the opinions of fre wyll / and the merit of works. You ſe now how nedefull yt ys for men to be armed / and to be ſtrong in the fayth / ſo waſtinge and wthſtode in theſe latter dayes / to be more oten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied in prayer and ſcripture then of cuſtome / ſeinge Sathan now whettens his hornes by Gods parmiſſion to goore the more dyrefully for our further exerciſe and tryall. And in charitie fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee as you may / that ſuche ſmothe parſons and papers do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2684:13"/>the poore ſymple ſo vnable to wthſtand there ſubtill and and paynted reaſons. For once ſtayned therewth they ſhall as hardly be delyvered / as the intangled byrd from the lyme buſhe / becauſe yt ys as a ruſtie cancker eatinge throw wthout recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie / by eyther gentle ople or the hard ſtele / no nor by the flaminge fyer / no more then there gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mother Ione Butcher could there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be reclaymed. And therefore yt ys wyſhed that neyther tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures nor violens to be vſed (yf aucthoritie ſo pleaſe) to there bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies / otherwyſe then banniſhement out of thoſe contreyes / by reaſon our noble Prince / Iudges / nor ſtate ſhould not be ſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of wth ſuche hard tearmes of Anabaptiſts and others as I on loth here to expreſſ and allreadie greved to heare what I deareby occaſion of report that one of this Englyſh company ys ſhortly lyke to die / beinge preſoner at Norwych. Beſides that there pertinacie and deſperate reſolution to ſuffer for there bad cauſes will intice the ignorant / not only to thinck that there out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagiouſe zoyle is a ſanctified zeale / proper onlie to the true mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs but lykewiſe to dowte the more of the Chriſtian faythe / and ſo make there diabolicall bowldnes to appere an holie ſuffringe and right martyrdome / where yt ys rather a ſtronge deluſion of Sathan who mightilie begyleth therby: for as Chriſt in theſe xvj. hundred peres ſpace hathe had moſte holie and conſtant martyrs in his churche: ſo the devill as an ape imitatinge every good thinge in the ſayde church / hathe lykewyſe many fauls and raſhe headed ſufferers in his malignant churche in all ages and now ys evident by the bowld Ieſuttes / chuſinge rather ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernlie to die in the defens of there abhominations / then to lyve in the Catholyke faythe / by cravinge pardon of the Prince for there tryed threaſons. Baulls preiſts ſuffred moche in there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſhe zeale to there fauls Gods whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſo lawnced ſkorched there fleſhe to the bones wth there kuyves. Did not Kinge Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes in a wicked zeale / cauſe his ſonnes to paſſ throw the fyer. Beſydes the hardynes of the Iacobins that ſlew the late. Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che kinge / and that deſperat murderer committinge the lyke to the Prince of Orrenge / who thoughe his fleſhe by gobbets was nipt of wth burnynge pyncheons / yet that greved hym not when he was could the Prince was diſpatched. The ſame ſubtill ſpirit that wrought then will no dowre worck the lyke giddines and ſelf blodſhed in the Anabaptiſts. But true martyrdome is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſinge by voyce and deathe for the defens of the three gloriouſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2684:14"/>parſons in one God / and for the mayntenans of Chriſt his debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and Immanitie in one parſon / and for his gloriouſe goſpell ſake. I eſteme ſuche kind of ſufferers no better then they that be aucthors of there owne death. St. Peter ſayethe / yf anie man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fir let hym ſuffer as a Chriſtian and not as an evill doer. I wyſh ſuche to thinck on Hackett his frantyke zeale lately executed in cheapſyde: ſince whoſe vilde death manie a good Chriſtian have bene no leſſ vmbraded and reproched / then the ſacred diſcipline mocked and deſpiſed. To conclude let vs confeſſ the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell entierlie in yt fullnes / and to the deathe ſtand to / that Chriſt hathe the ſubſtans of God and the ſubſtans of man / of hym ſelfe from above / and of David here beneathe / yet ſpottleſſ of our gilte. And therfore let vs ſolace our ſelves wth theſe words in the tenn of the Hebr. Seinge therfore brethern that by the blodd of Ieſus / we may be bowld to enter into the holye place by the new and lyvinge waye wch he hathe prepared for vs throw the vaile that ys his fleſhe. Wherein we ſe that the fleſhe of Chriſt dothe ſhew vs his devinitie as hidden vnder a vayle / wch otherwiſe we could not indure to behowld that ſplendor and glorie / by the wch vaile we are directed and ledd vnto God / as he ſayeth in Iohn xij. He that ſeythe me / ſeythe hym that ſent me: Wherfore / o heavie and faythfull hart vnder the burden of ſynn: chere vp thy ſelf: for aſmoche as our heavenlie father dothe graciouſely and frelie Impute Chriſt his righteouſenes vnto vs for to geve vs lyfe eternall / in that he behowldeth vs not in our ſelves / but in his ſonn: as contrarie wyſe he ſtrykinge hym our redemer for vs / and behouldinge vs in hym / dyd exempt vs from hell and condembnation. The wch imputation of righteouſenes commes not to vs by anie mixture of his vnſpotted humanitie wth ours ſo ſpotted / but by the vertu of his ſpirit / he ys in ſuche ſort vnited ſo nere vnto thoſe that apprehend hym by faythe / as he and they be one bodie / ſpirituallie Ioyned: for the ſubſtants of bodie and ſoule have nothinge commune wth this ſpirituall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage / but rather we are made his vnder the vertu of this vnton by fre Imputacion: as lykewyſe by Imputacion he and all his threaſures are ours / wch ys confirmed to the faythefull lovinge and fearinge God in the ſupper: eate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pfortablie of this meate / as alſo by readinge / marckinge and applieng. And ſeke out theſe texts to ſtrengthen thy ſelf and others: namely how Chriſt ys caulled the ſone of God and the ſonn of man: to have a father in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2684:14"/>heaven and a mother in yerthe. A child and a ſonn to be borne and geven vs. The word was God / and was made fleſhe. Tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Sede of David / and the ſonn of David. Chriſt deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the fathers after the fleſhe. He was in the fourme of God / and in the fourme of a ſervant. And in ſondry places caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſonn of Mary / David his lorde no leſſ then Davids ſonn: a woman compaſſed a man. Chriſt as a man dyd eate / drinck / ſlepe / was wery / and veryly died. And he bothe God and man / walked on the ſea / and cauſed the deade to come out of the grave / he ys Alpha and Omega: the rote of David / and the generation of David / wch ys playne two natures God and man. May I not ſay now wth the Apoſtle? O ye foliſhe and fonde conceyted Anabaptiſts / who hathe bewitched you? To denie this cheyfe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle the ſowndation of our Chriſtian faythe and the end of our ſalvation. God mollifie your hard harts / and make vs hartilie thanckfull for his truthe to vs revealed beinge our ſoveraigne happines / yf yt be preciouſelie eſtemed / and not ſlenderly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / or cowldly profeſſed. It behoves the Godly bothe in the Exchange / cittie and contrey to reade and to make more eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of reading of the ſcripture and the devine conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces from the ſame. that as you take tymes there / for buyenge and ſellinge / walkinge and communing / ſo in Gods behaulf and your owne / to obſerve the tymes of reading / prayenge / hearinge and of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge the Lorde / conſideringe the Apoſtle ſayeth / geve attendans to readinge / aſwell as to exhortation and doctrine. And note that fructeleſſ reading of vayne books from prophane aucthors is as hurtfull / as necgligent hearinge of the worde ys vnprofitable. The right vſe of wch two vertues ys to be traved of God: the one publykely by the office of the eare / and the other privat by vſe of the eye and tounge: and bothe to be nothinge wthout the will mynde and affection: Better therefore ys a ſhort and diligent readinge now and then wth good attencion / then to turn manie leaves wth ſmall regard and leſſ apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion. The holie Ghoſts in mercy open oure eares / diſpoſe our harts and guyde our tongs to theſe ends for Gods glorie and oure mutuall compforth / Amen. To the wch gloriouſe parſon we muſt often in theſe kinds make ſpeciall ſute vnto: for as his graciouſe preſens in hearinge and readinge dothe keye from vs wronge interpretacion / wery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and tediouſenes: ſo his abſens ys cauſe of the one and the other / with our diſprofict and greate anoye. At ſuche tymes then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2684:15"/>let vs crye / come holie Ghoſte / enleghten and ſupport our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans and weakenes: not that God the thryd parſon coeternall wth the father and the ſonn can be comprehended in any man / who is ſo incomprehencible of hym ſelf / but rather we deſire his effects / operation and working: as we ſe the manyfould beames procedinge from the bodie of the ſonn ſo farr diſtant from the yearth / dothe yet ſend downe her heate and power to all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And as I wyſhe you profitablie to reade and heare: ſo in walkinge in eyther Exchange / feyld or hows to remember to walk out your race and the reſt of your dayes more carefully and religiouſely to the Kyngdom of heaven warde: for the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God to our father Abraham that he ſhould walk ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilie before hym / dothe alſo appartayne to you his children by faythe that hope to be wth hym in glory: and ſo to practys He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zychia his ſacred prayer / ſayenge / I beſeche the o Lord remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how I have walked before the in truthe and wth a parfect hart. A prayer and leſſon worthie to be thought on ſeinge the Lorde no leſſ requireth this of vs then of the Iſralitiſhe church: ſayenge what dothe the Lorde thy God require of the / but to feare the Lorde thy God / to love and ſerue hym to walk in his wayes / and to cleaue vnto hym / as thoughe wthout wch ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge and cleavinge / he ys no nerer God to vs then to his vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall creatures. Wherfore as the Apoſtle ſayeth / yf we lyve of the ſpirit / let vs walke in the ſpirit. And to walke in this ſort ys to walke acceptablie and ſecurelie. My ſelf in greate weakenes walkinge ſum tymes in that worſhipfull hows: although I made there the beſt choyce I coulde of parſons and taulk for our mutuall good: yet my hart toung and eare ſlippinge ſo ofte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the due byas wth the loſſ of tyme wherein to have bene bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter occupied / makes me now to crave pardon of God / and thus publykely to confeſſ yt a fault vnto the world. And therfore good bretherne of ſuch loving acquayntans: as I am hartelie thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for your curteſie and gentlenes: ſo do I wiſhe that you oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie or ſpare that populouſe place / none otherwyſe but as caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and neceſſitie requirethe.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle exhorteth all to applie our ſelves to the tyme: the brevitie wherof conſidered / yt will haſten vs to Imploy the beſt exerciſes therein.<note place="margin">Tyme.</note> For as nothinge ys more preciouſe then the tyme: ſo of manie nothinge ys more vyldlie abuſed / and every thing more certayne then the continuans thereof. It lacks but a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2684:15"/>little of xvi. hundred yeres a go / ſithens St. Paull ſayde / the tyme ys but ſhort: then yt muſt nedes be ſo moche the more ſhorte now by ſo many yeres / wher vpon as all Godly changers wilbe the more quickned and awakened to Exchange there vnprofitable vſe of the tyme to a better: evenſo / I exhorte all miſſpenders / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſers and voluntarie necglecters of the tyme in that royall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change / ſo to change or caſt away that greate faulte in theme / as there right vſage of the tyme from this readinge forwards may be a teſtimonie of there true faythe and repentans: for tyme ys ſo preciouſe that yt muſt be redemed and ſtryven for. And thus Chriſtian reader I wyſhe you to eſteme moche and to devyde the tyme for ſeverall exerciſes therein / bothe for God / and for your ſelves / for Prince cittie and familie. No dowte the devill perſwades ſum carnall and viciouſe parſons that there tyme ys well ſpent / beinge vſuall in the taverne and that there Impietie ys cloſely covered when they do bable out a few cowld prayers / and come once a weke to the churche wthout regard of other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. As a daplie dronckard in Billeter lane / anſwered one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiringe his haſtie ryſinge the next daye: I muſt ſayde he haue a tyme to put on my clothes / a tyme to pray / and a tyme to ſett myne how ſhould in order. By whome we ſe that as all heritikes thinck theme ſelves to have the beſt religion and to be nereſt vnto God: ſo common dronckards and carnall lyvers / by ſum ſhew of civilitie eſteme theme ſelves as honeſt and as truly religiouſe as the beſt / and bothe by a ſubtill prompt of the divill. Who hathe fayre paynted hypocrites in the churche in the alchows / and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne dronkards / beſides adulterers / blaſphemers and robbers / all theſe will make ſhew of religion / and ſeme to love the churche and ſermon: but none otherwyſe then as ſum gay profeſſors (ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge ſecret minions) do love there wyues / more for fame and to a voyde ſhame / then for any right affection they beare to the one or the other. Theſe miſerable people will alſo come bowldly to the Exchange / and be no more a ſhamed to be there / then a frayed in the churche at the hearinge of Gods iudgements denownced againſt theme: becauſe for the tyme / they have no leſſ adamant harts wthout felinge / then braſen forheads wthout bluſſhinge. Nevertheleſſ beinge in the compaſſ of this freyndly exhortation: I beſeche you / as bretherne by creation / although not yet by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation to take ſorrow and greyf to hart / wth ſyedie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned repentans: that ſo you may be changed bothe in churche
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2684:16"/>hows / and in the Exchange from that you haue bene to that you ſhould be / tremblinge at Gods iudgements / and ſo hartylie to crave mercie and grace. Eſtemynge now a moſt dangerouſe thinge to think on to morrow / and to neglect this days conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Wyſhing you to forgeit no longer what ys written: except you be borne agayne you cannot enter into the Kyngdome of God. For yf you beleyue in Chriſt crucifyed / then muſt you be in better forte crucifyed wth hym / that ys to ſlay and mortifie thoſe enormities / whervy to haue the ſimilitude of his deathe by kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge ſuche groſe ſynnes / and alſo the ſimilitude of his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by ryſinge agayne in to the newnes of lyfe. The wch the Lord grant for his mercy ſake. Generally then all do ſtand in nede to begg and intreate that the feare of the Lorde be graven and grownded wthin our harts: the wch as yt ys the ſpirituall bytt to curbe vs back from ſuche execrations: ſo ys yt a devyne ſpurr to quicken vs forwards to all Chriſtian actions. The wch beinge abſent / ys ſurely the deathe of all vertue / the increaſe of all vyce / the ſhipwrack of conſcyens / and all confuſion in lyfe. Therfore bleſſed ys the man to whome the feare of the Lord ys granted / becauſe yt ys glory gladnes / reioyſinge and the Ioyfull crowne / as Sirack ſayeth / and that aſwell of the ritche and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as of the meane and poore. Vnderſtand not here ſuche a feare as the bondman ys of a tyrant / or a condemned theyfe of the Iudge / but as of a graciouſe childe / in feare and love to obey / that ys in beynge lothe to offend our good father and laſtinge lover / and alſo in feare of his rodd. So myxinge hope and feare to gethers as to feele an humble reuerens in our harts / to the God of correction and of merry / beinge Ioyfull and thanckfull when by grace we ceaſe to do evyll / and to do the good / and ſory and fearefull / yea pemtent and tearefull when by weakenes we be drawen to the contrary. And as every Chriſtian ought to crave and covet this ſinguler vertue: ſo to lament to ſe ſuche tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitudes and myſcheyfs aboute vs in the world / throw the want of this feare. Let vs then feare and ſerve the Lorde wth all our harts / as many as intend to be partakers of his glory: I ſpeake to theme vnto whome God hathe geven right eares to heare.</p>
               <p>Agayne ſum tymes the prowde and loftie do walke there to be ſene in there beyght and braverie / aſwell as others of good degre bothe men and wemen ſpend an hower there for neceſſitie of recreation.<note place="margin">Prowd.</note> And therfore they walkinge and wearinge in that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2684:16"/>common place agreable to there caullinge and ſtate / are not to be adiudged amonge ſuche prowd and loftie ſo over ſtately lokinge. Wyſhinge all infected parſons wth that greate and capitall ſynn changinge angells into devills haſtely to diſcerne that infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / wherbie in tyme to ſeke and fynd the remedie / and to eſteme there hawtie hart as a certame dronckennes / be witchinge or dullinge the ſame / ſo as neyther precept from God / nor dutie to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ys regarded: and yt procedeth from the aucthor of pryde / and by a fauls imagination of theme ſelves: the poſſeſſors whereof can neyther pray rightly to God / nor effectually heare the word / nor lyve quietlie and familierly wth there neighbors / moche leſſ to guyde there harts and tounges charitablie and orderly. God grant you then to hate and abhor pryde and to laugh yt to ſkorn / ſeinge there ys nothing more agaynſt true Godlynes and your ſalvation then the ſame / by reaſon yt beſotteth men and wemen / thruſtinge theme to raſhenes / vnrulines / and to take overmoche heade and bridle. And here let the beſt regenerat kepe in mynde / that this pryde will incrediblie lurck and be hydd in theme to there hurt / wthout good hede and watche / for that yt ys hard to be knowen in all things and at all tymes. I for beare to ſpeake moche of this ſubtill ſinn: but only towch ſuche dreggs and rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants therof as remayne in Gods children to kepe theme in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle / to ſtryue and wreſtle agaynſt yt / being to theme ſuche a ſtinge as yt prycketh and pyncheth / wowndeth and healeth (where the ſayde health by grace muſt conſequently follow) lyke fyer expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge fyer / or one ſynn healing another / as poyſon geves remedie to poyſon. Wherfore the better to know ſum ſubtiltie of that lurcking ſyun even in the Godly / whoſoever ys ſo ſtyffly opinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as to ſtande in there owne conceite / or lothe to be iuſtly and freindly reproved for there fault / or truſteth more in there owne wayes / then ruled vy advice and cowncell / or that glorie exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively for there well doinge / or that contend more for victorie in diſputacion or reſoninge / then to yelde to the playne truthe: they vndowtedly are ſtayned wth this pryde and had nede wth the aucthor to pray for a contrite / humble and lowlie hart. We ſhall never hate and ſhunn pryde / love and imbraſe humilitie to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis yt / before men narrowly viſite and ranſike there owne harts: wherby the better to know theme ſelves. At wch tyme behowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge the ſtorehows and heape of ſynn wthin vs / we ſhall the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtowpe and abaſe our gap plumes / and check downe the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2684:17"/>prowde hart ſo previlie ſckinge to mownt a lofte / and crie o duſt and aſhes cum back ſtay thy ſelf / and clymbe no hygher: by wch conſideration we will at lengthe confeſſ / that as pryde is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall and heade vice in wycked men: ſo humilitie ys the chifeſt vertu in the Godly / wthout wch fowndation all other vertues be blowen a waye wth the blaſt of vayneglorie / as duſt or fethers wth the wynde of the ayre. But as for the groſſ and common prowde (who as Iob ſayeth loke vp to the ſonne) ſo prowde as the pecock and as ſtowt as the lyon / exaltinge your ſelves and caſtinge downe others / the Prophet Eſaye cryeth againſt you / ſayenge the day of the Lorde ſhalbe on ſuche as be lyfted vp in there harts / vpon the highe Cedars of Liban / and on the greate okes of Baſan. Downe therfore / and be thinck that as waters ſtand not on highe mownt aynes / but ſekes downe to the low valleyes: ſo the graces of Gods ſpirit abydeth not in the loftie hart / but goeth into the humble and lowlie. The wch God in merrie grant to the writer and reader / to teachers and learners.</p>
               <p>The poore though they be neyther walkers nor dealers amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you / yet they paſſ to and fro through the Exchange / bothe the Godly poore / and prophane poore / the one vnder Gods bleſſing and favour / the other vnder his frowne and diſpleaſure / who thoughe they be rude and lewd / and as voyde of diſpoſition to learne / as of common knowlege amongeſt men:<note place="margin">Poore.</note> yet as the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God / they are not alone to be corrected and forced to labor / but to be pittied releved a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d helped / eſpecially the ſyck lame and aged amonge that ſort: aſſuringe your ſelves that we are none otherwyſe the children of God / then by doing good to ſuch as be vnworthie therof by Gods owne example cauſinge the ſonn and rayne to ſhew there nedefull efferts vpon bothe iuſt and vniuſt. For where the Apoſtle byndeth a ſpeciall good to be donn to the nedie in Gods hows / he excludeth not but commandeth the lyke to thoſe miſerable people notwthſtandinge they wth others ſeme to beginne there hell here / vntill the Lorde towche there harts wth repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tans and converſion: yet in the meane tyme we are to ſhew theme pittie and compaſſion. Moſte worthie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of this dutifull regard to all ſorts of poore I ſe in this towne of Harlem / even multitudes provided for every Lords daye / beſides hoſpitalls for men wemen and children wth ſick howſes for the diſeaſed / never none ſene to dye in the ſtrete or ſtarve vnder ſtall. The other kynd of poore be in and of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2684:17"/>churche / our bretherne and ſuſters / aſwell by the ſecond as the ſyrſt byrthe / gevinge your ſelves to prayer to labor and travell as you may for your mayntenans / and are aſhamed to be ſene beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge or cravinge in ſtrete or doore: there vp your ſelves / howld out and parſiſt to the end wth paciens vnder Gods croſſ / wth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eyther envyenge the ritche or grudgiuge agaynſt the Lorde / conſideringe Ieſus Chriſt hathe ſanctifyed the povertie of his poore / in that for there ſake he became poore hym ſelf. But ſe that you fele the inward povertie of the ſpirit / to be ioyned wth the outward / wherby to haue the bleſſinge pronownced in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell Bleſſed are the poore in ſpirit. The wch noble vertu ought to be deſirable to Lords ladies / and the greateſt Threaſurers in the world. That yf by grace thow haſte the rytches of the ſoule be never aſhamed nor greved / but rather humbled at the povertie of thy bodie. For thy head and Captayne was poore in his byrthe / in his lyfe and death / and previe to thie baſe eſtate becauſe he in wyſdome ordayned yt ſo: ſayeng by his ſervant St. Iohn / I know thy tribulation paciens and povertie. And you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull ritche / yt ys rather Chriſtian honor then any diſhonor to your degrees for to have now and then ſuche Godly poore at your tables to be made partakers of Gods creatures wth you / as havinge ſum intereſt in theme / and ſo to diſtinguiſh betwene the Lords ſpeciall poore and the prophane poore / and bothe to be ſuccoured for his ſake.</p>
               <p>Sum Printers and ſtacioners at certayne tymes haue there meting there / and therfore are wthin the compaſſ of this freynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gretinge.<note place="margin">Prynters.</note> Fyrſt I acknowledge the Arte to be moſte profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / excellent / and neceſſarie for church and common welthe / and God highly to be prayſed for revealinge that ſynguler knowledge vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and alſo to be prayed vnto for leſſ abuſe and more right vſe of the ſame / by Printinge and fellinge ſuche good bookes grownded on ſcripture as in creaſe knowledge / vertu and the feare of God / no leſſ then for the mayntenans of laws and civill order. But as the greate nomber of Printers haue compiled more bookes then men haue braynes to conceyue / memories to retayne / or money to buy: ſo the multitude of there worcks over dulleth and burdeneth / and ys a greate ſtopp to the beſt and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt readings. And therfore for the better vttera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſo many ydle bookes in ſhopps and ſtalls / me thincks (in good pollicie) the wyſe and worſhipfull ſorte of that compame might do well to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2684:18"/>procure a ſtaye and ſum reſt to be had for there over werped preſſes / but eſpecially for mens weake memories. For manie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie wytts practys to followe good writers / and to the greate hurt of the churche do make huge heapes or cartlodes of fond and folyſhe bookes / from the wch fault I eſteme the Godly Printer to be free / and therfore he hym ſelf ys to be well eſtemed of as his good travell and labor to be commended. But ſuche of that caullinge in my natyve contrey as haue neyther care nor conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to print and publiſhe vayne and vnprofitable / prophane and hurtfull pamphletes to the offens of God and men / fillinge the peoples heades / emptieng there purſes wth the abuſe of there eyes and eares / by there fables or ſkoſſinge devices / are bothe to be reproved and reſtrayned. For as God hathe his holy and learned ſervants in citties and contreyes / that ſtudie and penne forthe worthie worcks for his glorie and to the benefirt of his church: ſo the devill / hathe his ſeducing ſecretaries or pennſlaves in ſecret corners to ſerve the humors of ſuche had inſtruments / and the affections of rude readers. I have knowen in Powles churche yarde ſum perilouſe aſwell as popiſh and ſuperſticiouſe bookes ſould previly to the yll diſpoſed by ſuche as I pray God to geue theme true repentans.</p>
               <p>Shipmaiſters and maryners of good intereſt in the exchang / you alſo be nedefull members for Prynce / people and ſtate / ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turinge your ſhips goods and lyves by tranſporting of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities from ſundry contreyes and nations / behowldinge more plentie of Gods wonderfull worcks / his corrections and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances / his helpe at a pinche to ſum / and his ſodaine and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Iuſtis to others / and therfore the more bownd to dread and feare hym as a Iudge and Lord / to obey hym as our ſoveraigne mayſter / and to loue hym as a favorable father / who returninge you ſaufe to contrey / wyfe / and acquayntants:<note place="margin">Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers.</note> then as Noye eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge the greate flod dyd buyld an alter and offred to the Lorde: ſo you to offer hartie thancks / to reioyce and to lyve in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / to ſtand ſtill on your watch and to remember that you muſt to the Sea agayne to abyde all tydes and weather. For they that ſerve the Lorde / and avoyde ryot in the quyet haven / ſhall ſurely be hearde and helped in the tyme of ſtorme. In all my tyme on ſeaboorde (the Lords greate ſchoule howſe) as I have knowen no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers that were of another diſpoſition: ſo I truſt the tyme hath not changed you yet lyvinge / as yt hathe donn ſum others chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2684:18"/>lyke the moone. The Sea was the fyrſt correctinge prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher / for the ſpace of xvj. yeres / wch caulled me from moche fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie / and that gave ſum entrans to know and feare the Lord: and therfore amongſt ſo many learned and lyvinge preachers / bleſſed be his name for the Sea my dumbe and fearefull teacher: in wch navigable arte I ſpent the pryme of myne peres when ſchole had bene more firt / yf habilitie had ſerved: wch will not ſuffer me to forget that wch I would you ever to remember / namely that God is merveylouſe in all his worcks and worthie to be moche thought on / in your Sea ſtormes / ſwellinge waves / croſſ tydes / dangerouſe races / longe travers in contrarie wynds / the ſhip on hull / the heline on lee / full hawſe in tumbling roades / when ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack is fearedwthout faſt howld of cable and aricker / ſtepeleſſ and fearefull nights / fower beere and beanes ofte tymes in ſteade of byſkett / cowld watches and wett clothes paynefull and pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge leakes / hale bollinge to double the poynt / a luff from the rock / rowmer from the ſand / ſteere at an yuch / or miſſ the haven / a fogg / at the entrans / ſtorme and bellow on poope / beſyde myne acquayntans wth your ſprung maſts / torne ſales from the parde and ſuche lyke quicknings to draw all maryners nere vnto God / or to harden theme further of to the devill / as ſchollers eyther bettered or made worce by correction: for as ſum roote of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes draweth the Godly to be more Godly / ſo that begon roote not beinge norriſhed as fyer wth wodd / yt becomes weaker and vaniſheth at lengthe tyll they be ſylthie and more fylthie / yea a traytor to all goodnes as Iudas to his mayſter. Wherfore lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge mates and bretherne / bethinck that the crowne of glorie is ſet forthe vnto vs neyther in the beginninge nor in the middeſt / but in the end of the race. Sathan and fleſh caſt many blocks in our way not alone to hynder vs from the holy parſeverans / after we haue runnthe greater part of the waye / but ſumtymes to breake of ſodaynly mens good begynnings. Our cheyfe ſtryving muſt be for parſeverans / and the ſame wth good courage / for the crowne that we ſtrive and labor for / ys worthie of running. The Apoſtle to Timoth. ſayeth / continew thow in the things wch thow haſte learned. And the Hebr. ſayeth / that we are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſt yf we kepe ſure vnto the end that begynninge / wherewth we are vpho wlden. Let vs then learne to complaine agaynſte the burden of our corruptions / for that they hynder our marchinge forwards vnto goodnes. For the pithe and ſubſtans
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2684:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2684:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2684:20"/>of our Chriſtian race is to perſeuere in the fructes of repentans and in the effectes of our holy profeſſion. Let vs wthall loke wel on the compaſſ poynt directinge to the haven / that ſo we may ſteere right and howld on our courſe thether wards / and though now and then we make pawes agaynſte our wills / yet let vs not therfore geve over / but to the helme agayne and take better hede of our ſterage / puttinge on more bonets and to hoyſe vp the ſayles / for to breake agaynſt the ſtrong and contrary tyde.</p>
               <p>Now and then valiant Captaynes and Gentlemen ſouldiers come thether to take there pleaſure amonge you / whoſe valure and venturable ſervys for Prince and ſtate / deſervethe the favour and good wyll of all true ſubiects.<note place="margin">Captay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note> For who but they vnder God (endowed wth courrage and Captaynely knowlege) that muſt ſtand betwene court / cittie / and contrey / and the cruell force or deſperate aſſault of the enemie? who but they do take there lyves in there hands / and runn on the poynte of the pykes for the love of our Soverainge and commons / ſuſtayning the deadly ſtrokes of the bullet / and do thruſt in a mydd the flaſhinge ſwerds and pykes? who but they cowld abyde ſuche hunger and colde / watch and be wett / abyde the roringe canons and thundring culverins / wth the downefall of there terrible ſhotts on there pates and ſum tymes throw there breſts or bowells / beſydes the lynger of paye ſycknes and mortalitie? Theſe are the bowlde bullwarcks that fight and faſt / when you be quiet and merie at your diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of meates and drincks: who muſt wake and moyle / when you ſlepe and walke at pleaſure / and gladder of the courfeſt breade and the runninge water / then many ritche be thanck full wth the fineſt diet / and beſt wyne or beere. Wherfore let all ſtates and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees eſteme of ſerviceable Captaines / Gentlemen ſouldiers / and there trayned inferiors accordinge to there valure and demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure vnder military diſcipline / and lykewyſe willingly wthout grudge to yeld to ſuche taxations and payments / wch muſt be levied for there mayntenans to defend all againſt the prowde and bloddie ſpanyards / intendinge to make ryvers of Engliſhe blodd yf they might: But I truſt the Sea ſhall fyrſt devowre thoſe ſhips and cruell companie. Now you worthie ſervitors bothe on ſea and land / of ſuche reſolution to dye vnder the ſayde combatts and conflicts: I beſeche you ſett before your eyes / the moſte honorable cauſes of your adventures / wherby to be the more magnaminiouſe and conſtant / and for your better felinge
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2684:20"/>of inward compforthe at the hower of your quick diſpatche: to were that you fight for the true honor of your moſte marvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe and mercifull God / for the glory and mayntenans of the heavenly goſpell of his ſonn Chriſt / for your Soveraigne Lady defendrix vnder God of the ſame / and for your native and noble contreye her Maces dominions. All theſe famows reſpects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge graffed in your harts / wth fayth and repentans for ſinnes / then may you valiantly marche / vnder the helmet of ſalvation / and the armure of prayer / after dromme / fyfe and trompett that pleaſant and warlyke muſike / and that wth courrage and ioye / wth ſure truſt and confidens that the Lord of hoſtes ys wth you and on your ſyde becauſe you fyght vnder the Lords banner / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Antichriſt and his bloddy band. In the meane tyme / you worthie Captayned / Leyvetenants and other Gentlemen of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis / ſe that you magnifie God and his true religion / by beynge ſtudiouſe to be religiouſe and Godly in lyfe / wthout yeldinge to whoredom dronckennes / blaſphamie / quarrellinge or ſuche lyke: and to reſtrayne thoſe vices aſmoche as you may in others. For as the ſtrengthe of the ſouldier conſiſtethe in the wyſdome of the Captayne / ſo the right cariage of ſouldyers / is moche drawen from the good behavior of there Captaynes and guydes. And in vſing of militarie correction on your poore ſouldiers / let clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and good diſcreation be ioyned wth Juſtis / ſekinge rather to remove the cauſes of there mutterings / then to vſe ſeveritie vp ſodayne parturbations / ſtudieng no leſſ to be favoured and loved then to be breade and feared of your companyes / and finally (for to bringe honor and good fame to your Princes pay / aſwell as credite to your ſelves) yeld the poore creatures there due wages to buye theme victualls for there more ſtowt ſtandinge in her Maieſtis ſervice wthout could quakinge / or compulſion of ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge through want therof.</p>
               <p>And you that be common ſouldiers / love your Prince / obey your Captaynes / be contented wth your wages / avoyde fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge and robbinge: and conſider what baddnes and lewdnes ys layed every where to your charge / ſo as by your yll behavior the worthie name of a ſouldier is bothe lothed and ſhunned. For what vyldnes and wyckednes is not fownd in many of you? beinge cownted the ſkumm and droſſ of the world / by your forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations chrietie / tearinge of the bodie of Chriſt / your ſtealing and murderinge to come by your pray. O my contrey men I pray
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2684:21"/>you waxe wery of theſe horrible qualities / ere the ſhott of greate or ſmall ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s teare in peces your wretched carkaſes to make ſpedie paſſage for your impenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſouls to be ſodainly partakers of helliſhe torments. Repente therfore and learne to know God / in ſteade you be thought Godleſſ / ſpare and ſaue your wages to ſerve your pinchinge neceſſities / and not ſo horriblie to waſte your money / to the diſtruction of bodie and ſoule: that ſo God may be mercifull to you in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And althoughe warrs be the ordinans of God / and therfore is caulled the Lorde of hoſtes / or the God of batteyls / being one of his plagues due for our ſinnes:<note place="margin">Of Warrs.</note> yet we are to pray hartily to God for our deliverans from warr / and to obtayne peace and concorde in ſteade of it: the terror wherof ſhould make vs to groane and to pray wth greate longinge for the ſpedie comming of our redemption / aſwell for our ſeaſing to ſinne / as for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie layd vp in ſtore for vs. By the wch lawfull and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie peace / our lands to be tylled / our feylds and cattle to floriſh / our ſede for proviſion to be ſowen / our vyneyards planted and then to enioy the reapinge and mery harveſt wth the pleaſant vintage: In ſhort all to lyve vnder orders and lawes / in amitie and vnitie: where contrary wyſe warrs and diſcentions forrayn or civill is moſte hydeouſe and fearefull / full of wrathe blodd and ſlaughter / the feylds lyenge covered wth deade carcaſſes / citties and townes ſacked and ruyned / corne and graff trampled and waſted / famine and hunger / cryenge and lamenting on every ſide virgyns and wyves horriblie raviſhed / lawes and religion no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſett by / the ſlave and the raſcall to raynge and to triumphe over the civill and worſhipfull. All wch terrible ſkourges conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered / yt ſhould make all to looke to our lyves / to repent the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſe of the ſame / to craue pardon / and to ſaye <hi>Da pacem Domine.</hi> Seing now that God doth ſend warrs / and famine / ſicknes and mortalitie for our puniſhements / and that no ſuche afflictions can come into the cittie wthout the Lords ſendinge. The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts are outrageouſe by there raſhe ſenſures to condemne warrs and warrlyke affaires / or the ſouldiers obediens to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therein / whether offenſive or defenſive / and that vnder collor that we in the goſpell ſhould not warr as the Iſralites dyd: wherin they neyther reſpect the providens and ordinans of God in this / nor the greate deſert of there ſinnes wth ours procuringe the ſwerde. Beſydes that they do greatly abuſe theſe words / law
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2684:21"/>and goſpell ſeperatinge theme further a ſunder / then they ought / foraſmoche as the goſpell was in the law / and the law in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / ſeinge the goſpell was from Abam. Secondly they deceyve theme ſelves in this vſe of warrs by a fauls underſtandinge of Chriſt his reprehencion to Peter drawinge forthe his ſwerde / whervpon they conclude that Maieſtrates ought neyther to warr / nor to puniſhe malefactors wth deathe. Surely Princes and all Eſtates are ſmally behowlde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuche fauls teachers and erroniouſe people for maynteyninge thoſe dangerouſe opinions agaynſt Maieſtracie in theſe ſpaniſhe warrs / aſwell as notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe heriſies agaynſt the articles of the Chriſtian faythe: Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States ſpendinge there threaſures and people in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fens of theme and there goods aſwell as in ours / otherwyſe bothe clamerouſe Anabaptiſts and Papiſts ſhould no leſſ be ſwallowed vp of the enemie / then vs the profeſſors of Chriſt his religion. God make theme leſſ contemptible and more thankfull wth vs for the Lords Leyvetenants vpon yerthe.</p>
               <p>Now to the ſpirituall warr / wherein we muſt be all exerciſed ſouldiers / if we looke to be partakers of Gods Kingdom / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of our ſavior Chriſt the Lord of true peace ſpeaketh / ſayenge I came not to ſend peace in to the yerthe but warr:<note place="margin">Spirituall warr.</note> in wch kynd of warr he appoynted none other weapons then thus / he that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not vp his croſſ and follow me ys not worthie to be my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple / ordayninge the chefeſt poynt of this warr to conſiſt in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe iniuries / and not in doinge theme. Well we muſt become ſpirituall warriors and fight vnder Chriſt his enſigne wth the complete armure mentioned by his worthie warrior S. Paul: ſayenge put on the whole armor of God that you may be able to refiſt in the evell day: remember that in baytyſme we bownd our ſelves ſo to become Chriſtian ſouldiers / as continually to fight agaynſt ſuche mightie enemis / as never ceaſe the crafty aſſaults but ever ſeke to ſcale the walls of our poore ſoules / wth whome to take peace / is to breake the truce and covenant betwene vs and our heavenly Captayne to our vtter deſtruction. Let vs not then ſnarle and intangle our ſelves wth over moche toyle and care of the world / that ſo we may the more eaſily pleaſe him that hathe choſen vs to be fyghtinge ſouldiers. Chriſtian reader note well this / ſeinge by ſlender footing in the Lords feylde many on every ſyde / do take ſuche foyles and deadly wownds / as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from there ſouldierly ranck / by necglect of armure and by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2684:22"/>faynines of fight in the tyme of aſſault: but let vs be ready to ſay wth the Apoſtle / at the ſurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drie of our laſt gaſpe: I have fought a good fyght / I have finiſhed my courſe / kept the fayth and then the crowne of glory ſhalbe ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Muſers on Gods provides.</note>There vs another ſorte walkinge there betwene the ordinary howers of the Exchange / who be greate muſers on Gods longs ſuffringe / and on his highe providens by weakenes of fayth and knowlege / being racked and troubled to be howld ſum egregious wycked men to have the fayreſt ſhew and greateſt floriſhe / and therfore do marvell on Gods longe ſuffringe. At wth common block many weakelings do ſtumble / when they ſe the Lord one while to delaye his puniſhements / another while haſtily to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame / and next in that he putts of the fuccouringe of his churche / or ſum diſtreſſed member thereof: not conſideringe the words in Tim. <hi>5.</hi> ſum mens ſinnes are open before hand / and go before vnto iudgement / and ſum ſinnes follow after. We muſt beare wth that wch the Lord thinks not good by and by to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect / nor to geve the remedie or ſuccor when we lyft / but when he hym ſelf will. Agayne ſum mens enormities are diſcouvered and come vnto iudgement ſoner then men loked for: and others be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and puniſhed alonge tyme after / as though yt ſlept. But albeit Gods gentle chaſticements or heavie iudgements do not haſten theme ſelves / yet they come on / thoughe ſayre and ſoftlie after. Symon the ſorcerer his ſinnes came before hande / whyle Saul / Iudas and other hypocrites there finnes came after / and were detected at length / thoughe for a tyme they deceyved many / evenſo Godlynes holynes and vertu have there tymes limited of commendation and fame / and although it be long fyrſt by reaſon of ſum clowde obſcuringe theme for the tyme / yet in comminge they come and bring the greater ioye / therfore ſtandfaſt and faint not. And further to anſwere fuche weake parſons ſo ready to ſtumble at this poynt: the <hi>13.</hi> of Eſaye ſpeakethe of the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Babylonpans / as though it were preſently to be donn when in dede yt fell out more then <hi>200.</hi> yeres after: ſayenge the day of the Lorde is at hand / meaninge the tyme of the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall extermination vy Eprus ſo long tyme ere it came: the wch ſcripturely phraſes of preſent ſpeches / for things to come ys to be vnderſtand / fyrſt that the events and decrees of the Lorde do not paſſ beyonde the tyme of hym prefixed and limited / but ſhall as certainely come to paſſ as of they were already. For that wch
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2684:22"/>was don from Adam almoſte <hi>5600.</hi> yeres a go / and that wch ſhalbe from hence to the worlds end yt ys preſent before God / becauſe S. Peter ſayeth / one day before the Lord ys as a thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand peres: and Abacut <hi>2.</hi> ſayeth / the viſion is yet differred to a cectayne tyme / ſpeakinge of that wch he wyll finiſh wthout any fayle / ſapenge thoughe yt tarry / wayte / for yt ſhall come and not ſtaye. Wth ys bothe a compforth and a terror to dyvers ſorts of parſons: quayle not brother vnd thy croſſ / for the <hi>8.</hi> of No. ſayeth I eſteme that the afflictions of this tyme are not worthie of the glorie that ſhalbe ſhewed on vs / and <hi>4.</hi> of the Cor. for our light affliction wch is but for a moment cauſethe vnto vs a farr more excellent and aneternall wayght of glorie. Wherfore ceaſe thy admirations on Gods louge ſuffrings and providens / neyther mervell any more why God delayeth his help or ſuccor ſum tymes from his people: for in Eſaye his tyme the faythefull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>howldinge Senacharib to be victoriouſe over dyvers people in Iudea / and parceyvinge the churche of God vpon the poynt of vtter ruym / they in lyke weakenes thought thus in effect: Eſay hathe promiſed vs eaſe and deliverans / but when ſhall this come to paſſ? the Prophet intendinge to remidie ſuche a temptacion in the <hi>18.</hi> Chap. dothe conſent that there ſhalbe ſum delaye: but wthall he promiſeth two things in Gods behaulf / fyrſt that the churche ſhall be preſerved / in the myddeſt of the greateſt danger / next that yt ſhall ſurely be delivered / and ſo ſayethe that the churche will make a ſolemne reknowledginge of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towards yt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Miniſters.</note> I have many tymes beheld certayne miniſters reſort to that common plaſe / though very ſeldome ſene there any learned prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher / whome I know to be as carefull and dutifull / as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer careleſſ and vnprofitable / and therfore the more nede of this freyndly warninge / for to be leſſ in the Exchange / and of tener in the pulpet: rather in there ſtudies to prepare ſownd doctryne for mens foules / then amonge marchants to vſe tounge and eare abowt vncertayne news. Your ſtandinge / and mayntenants ys to be more watch full and paynefull for your ſeverall flocks / who as they yelde you large portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of there te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall things: ſo ought you be as liverall to theme in devine and ſpiritual things / wch can not be but by your better attendans on Godly ſtudies. Be not lyke ſuche dumbe and ydle loyterers in the contreys as think the readinge of there ſervice to be as ſufficient a diſcharge for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2684:23"/>theme as meate good ynoughe for there people: rather reſemble ſuche ſtudiouſe labourers / as premeditate for doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortarion / and as carefull for good lyfe and converſation. I wyſhe you made more conſciens / in takinge ſo moche for ſo ſmal payne / and in that you buyld eyther little or nothinge vpon the fowndation mentioned by S. Paul: vpon the wch ſum do laye gould / ſilver / preciouſe ſtones and tymber / and you eyther hay ſtubble or worce matter. The Lord quicken ſuche that they may be fownd buylders and furtherers / and not deſtroyers or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers / wth Vrim and Thumin / knowlege and vertu for to ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and hely forwards ignorant foules to the Kyngdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Conſider the better on your mutenes or baſe handlinge of the text / by hearinge in many pulpetts the ſwere ſownd of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned doctrine from the yong and forward youthes but peſter day out of the Vniverſities / wch ſhould rather make you emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to be nerer there good begynnings / then eyther to envie the ſame or to continew at a ſtaye. Wherfore pray to the holy Ghoſt fyrſt to pardon your former negligens / next in mercie to awaken you / wherby to offer vnto God more quyck ſacrifices and chaſts Vyrgins to Chriſt by your diligens and vigilacie / leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe you lye more open to Gods diſpleaſure / fyrſt for bearinge the name to be that you are not: next for kepinge out of thoſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings ſuche good ſchollers and Godly men as would be more paynefull and gayneful to yourpoore flocks compelled as ſhepe to leape over your greate hedges from the hard fallow to grene and better Paſture.</p>
               <p>Now muſt I make you previe of a ſubtill and craftie deceyver amongſt you / bothe marchants and others:<note place="margin">Deceyver.</note> who as he will take intereſt in the Exchange / not muſſingz his lurckinge and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge in that plaſe: evenſo to often he prevayleth and gaynethe. Beinge once a chayned flave / next / ſett at livertie and ys ſuche a conning Iuggler as wthout moche a do you can not eſcape his leger demaines: I meane the devill ſo inviſible and prowde an intruder / as he dare walk not a lone amonge marchants / but in Princes courts / and a middeſt the beſt occupied aſſemblies in your cittie. This fellow begann his prybe and envie in heaven / retaynes it in hell / and foweth it abrode in the world / who ſo powerfully worcketh as the Apoſtle tearmes hym the God of this world / by reaſon his kingly regiment (by permiſſion of the true and righteouſe God) ys amonge yerthlie and worldly myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2684:23"/>men more lyke the blynd mowle in the low grownd / then the pleaſant lartk a lofte in the ſkie. This wylie feynd geves not his onſect after his vglie and terrible maner / but by fyne fatches and angelicall inſinuation / ſo experimented of mens diſpoſitions by longe continuans / as lyke the fiſher he hathe a contrarie bayte for ſundrie hookes a ſlaight for every ſinn / and a temptacion for all ſorts of people. And whome he once gettethe wth full fange into his gripinge clowches he howldeth faſter then catt the mowce norriſhing and fittinge theme for his pallaſe or dungeon / as the holy ſpirit frameth Gods children for the Kingdom of glorie. Now to diſcribe further to my friends of this inviſible changer: Vnderſtand that the devill is an Angell ſeperated from Gyd by pryde / a very nere and provokinge companion of the fleſhe / ſtirringe it forward to wyckednes / and drawinge it back from goodnes: the aucthor of murther / threaſons and envy / the roote of malys / and the heade of all miſcheife / ſo expert in his trade and proceding in all artes as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make greate enormities to ſeme but light / and fooles to think theme ſelves wyſe / the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt danger to appere none at all / and bitter things to taſte ſwete / makinge heryſie to appeee veritie / obſtinate ſtandinge to be true martyrdome / and the prowde parſon to thinck hym ſelf humble. Agapne note that he rather intycethe the conſent of the mynde / then enforſinge or conſtrayning the ſame / and yet he is cruell ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till / moſte ſpitefull and enviouſe. In all wch good bretherne I truſt yon will rowſe vp ſecure nature and take a freſhe occaſion to add prayer to prayer / to redeme the tyme / to apply your ſelves to the ſame / and to eſteme better of your ſpirituall armure / to make reſiſtans rather in the fyrſt then ſecond aſſault / eſpecially when that conninge Cooke goeth abowte to ſweten ſinn and to make it dulce and pleaſant in the taſte / as men cover ratts bane vnder ſuger or hony / ſo that this compaffer can moſt finely ſawce ſynne / and make ranck poyſon to ſeme a pleaſant morſell / as he dyd the fayre apple to our greate grand mother Eve / and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall bread and wyne / to be thought foode of lyfe to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie receyver / as to Iudas and ſuche lyke. This fyne cooke vs buſie every where to make ſwete morſells as his alluringe baytes to his hydden hookes. For example / whoremongers and ſuche carnall parſons / ſuffring theme ſelves wthout the fyrſt reſiſtans to be chafed by ther luſts / thene Sathan comes wth his tempered ſawce and conninge compownds wherby he makes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2684:24"/>that ſytute of concupiſcens to ſeme ſo delightfull as they affect and imbraſe yt to there lyves and / what thundringe ſoever the ſcripture ſownds agaynſt yt / wth the lyke to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon dronckards / whoſe toſſed cupp ys ſo ſpiced and tempered wth there mayſters arte / as they dare defie bothe lawes devine and humane / deſpiſe Sermons / wyfe and freinde reprovinge theme for there fault. Of the wch ſathanicall ſouldiers there be dyvers ſorts / as night dronckards / raylinge and ſtrykinge wretches of there wyves / children and ſervants / who are fayne to runn into corners and hoales to avoyde there madd dronckennes. God geve ſuche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentans. In fine let vs all be warned that Sathans wyles / for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in his owne ſhopp be infinite / and therfore yt behoveth chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers / Cytezins / and contrey to ſtande on there garde / ſeinge this mercyleſſ lyon vnder Angelical ſhew lyeth in previe wayt to catch and intrapp at every turne. But thow tremblinge and fearefull Chriſtian throwen downe by the felinge of thy ſynne / no leſſ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirouſe to be freed from the burden therof then afrayed to offend the Lord thy God / be thow of good chere wthout tormenting of thy felinge conſciens / forasmoche as by fayth and grace Sathan hathe no part nor portion in the / hating and ſhunninge ſynne / but rather / on theme that love and frequent ſynne / ſeinge Ieſus Chriſt wthout all ſtayne of ſynn became ſynn for the / that ys toke on hym thy ſinnfull deſerts / even vndergoinge the torments of hell and deathe in his bleſſed body and ſoule for thy ſake and thy moſte happie deliverans from bothe / therfore be not only daylie and hartilie thanckfull for this expiation of thy ſinn / but butifully watche and pray agaynſt the dreggs and remnants of ſinn lefte in the for to ſtryve and fyght to the end: Although the ſtrengthe and forte therof was broken I ſaye by Chriſt and faſtned to his croſſ to the everlaſtinge compforthe of all ſuche as love and feare the Lord / and be lothe to offend hym by there ſynne.</p>
               <p>Huſbands and wyves of all ſorts / lykewyſe have there plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable walkinge there at convenient tymes / whoſe honorable eſtate ſo dignified by the Sonne of God / I muſt not forgette but put you in mynd of that famouſe vnion ordayned of hym / that is two in one fleſhe / and therefore to be of one mynde in the Lorde and for theme ſelves.<note place="margin">Mariage.</note> And generally yt muſt putt all the faythfull in remembrans of the more happie vnion and moſte bleſſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage betwene Ieſus Chriſt and his churche / and every ſoule of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2684:24"/>his electe therein / beinge an vnſeparable bonde / and knytt faſter then all bonds amonge men / and a love beyond all loves / for ſo gloriouſe and Princely a ſpowze / to take and imbraſe ſo poore and meane an eſpowzes / even the higheſt to abaſe hym ſelf to the loweſt. O memorable love and humilitie deſervinge all prayſe and obedyens in all faythfull parſons bothe maryed and vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. And as neyther water nor any flodds are able to quenche or to drowne this love: ſo let neyther carnall love in the one / nor love of the world in the other be ever able to quenche or to drowne there love and lovely harts / to this our true lover / the fowntayne of all love. St Iohn ſayeth he that loveth not / knowth not God: for as the ignorans of God is the cauſe / why he ys not loved: ſo the knowledge of God producethe love to hym / and therfore ſo farr do we love God / as we know God / whereby yt ys playne that they who ſeke not to know God / can neyther truely nor rightly love hym. And I have noted ſum tymes in men and we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who never opened booke / that the love of God was more ſhed abrode in there harts / then in many that are puffed vp wth wynde knowledge. Hartilie wiſhinge maryed folkes no leſſ to mark and diſgeſt / then to reade the words of the Apoſtle / in caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge on man and wyfe to love one a nother / by example of Chriſt his incomparable love to his churche in that he gave hym ſelf for yt / clenſed and ſanctifyed yt. Then would yt in creaſe there affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and abate there diſcentions / and generally make bothe theme the better to love one another and all others of that my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall bodie to reioyce and be tenfowld more thanckfull for that ſpirituall coniunction / namely that beggers bratts of no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to be maryed and cowpled to ſuche a heavenly huſband: whome the <hi>45.</hi> Pſa. tearmeth a Quene / ſayenge vpon thy right hand ys the Quene in a veſture of gould / and the canticles ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Chriſt his love to his churche and people / ſayeth his lefte hand ys vnder my heade / and his right hand dothe imbraſe me / wch mariageable tearmes by the holy Ghoſte / teacheth all / but more ſpecially huſbands and wyves to be ſo lyncked in love as to lyve and love to gethers moſt affectionatly and lovingly wth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eyther ſeperation of bodies / diſiunction of mynds or to lyve vnder iarrs and contencions to gethers to the ſeperation of God and Chriſt from ſum ſuche harts and howſes in London / as my ſelf and others have bene weryed and greved in laboringe for peace. But you Chriſtian yokefellows of a contrary diſpoſition / 
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2684:25"/>I wyſhe you by diſcreation and good watche to beware of ſuche fearefull diſcords / doinge your beſt to love ſtyll and to increaſe in love. For as love ys the capitall affection in men and wemen / ſo the effects therof ys moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / as ys confirmed by Chriſt his words: where a mans threaſure ys there is his hart / that is yf God be our heavenly threaſure / then ys our love a bove wth hym / yf maried folkes be corporal threaſures one to the other / then the love and affection ſpreadeth accordingly / as we ſe perth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mynded men have there love on yerthly things. You that be maryed parſons / Iplie as that tytle by the holy Ghoſte ys tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med honorable / ſo let your love / yeace and vnitie to gethers / ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and dignifie that lawdable eſtate. For as Chriſt cowld not chuſe any creature more apt to expreſſ our ſpirituall manduta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his fleſhe and blod / then breade and wyne: ſo the holy Ghoſte could not fynde a more apte ſimilitude to expreſſ the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bonde betwene Chriſt and every faythfull ſoule / then the coniunction of two parſons by the knott of matrymonie. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as mariage ys a moſte compfortable and bleſſed eſtate to theme who are graced to vſe yt well: ſo ys yt a moſte bitter and tormentuouſe eſtate to ſuch as love not to gethers / and as crave not for grace rightly to vſe yt. Now bothe worſhipfull and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun aſſemblie / ordinarie and extraordinarie changers in that Ropall hows / I beſeche you to remember / that as your lyfe here is vncertayne and never in one ſtaye / but lyke to the moone ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to chang and alteration and in the end to death: evenſo think that you muſt ſhortlie cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this lyfe for a nother / lyke your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors walking wth you as yeſterday / and now gonn and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: wch muſt put you in mynde to be ſo changed in affection and converſation / as when the Lords change bell ys runge to make ſpedie change of the place where you are / to a nother wth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any nayt / that ſo you may fynde the happie and better Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for this miſerable and worce / throw the ſame Ieſus Chriſt here after deſcrybed by a learned father / worthie of marchinge in this tyme of fauls Chriſts.</p>
               <p>Yt ys nedefull ſayethe he to vnderſtand how God was borne / and how God dyed according as the toung of the ſcripture dothe vſe to ſpeake:<note place="margin">God-man.</note> wch ſpeche of Chriſt ys dybersly before and after his incarnation. For ſince that happie and miraculouſe concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the holy Ghoſte / we muſt remember that in this vnitie of parſon (by the wch the ſonn of God is alſo the ſonn of Marie / 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2684:25"/>and by conſequent the very Sonne of man / that the two natures remaine diſtinct wth that wch ys proper to theme / and yet to be but one Chriſt / beinge hym ſelf God-man that ys Man-god / and yet notwthſtandinge his Deitie ys not his humanitie / nor his humanitie is not his Deitie. This beinge moſte true it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowth / that the proprieties of the humanitie (as to be borne / to eate / drinch to die and to be buried) ought to be attributed to God / I meane the ſecond parſon: and yet not ſimplie according to his Devinitie / but in aſmoche as he ys God-man: and on the other ſyde / that wch is proper to god / may be attributed to this man / as to be the Sonne of God / eternall / almightie / and to be ever all not ſimplie in his humanitie / but in aſmoche as he ys Man-God. The wch ſcripturely ſpeche S. Paul vſeth thus that the God of glory was crucified: agayne that God redemed the church by his blodd: and S. Luke ſayeth / that wch was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyved in the wombe of the Virgin / was the Sonne of the moſt highe: and therfore yt may be ſayde that Marie was the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God / in aſmoche as he was Man-god. That yf he wch was ſo conceyved and borne were not verie God / how ſhould he be our ſaviour: and yf the ſame were ſo ſpoken in regard of his Deitie / what maner of Deitie ſhould that be to take his Deitie in the Virgins wombe. As on the other ſide all the ſuffrings at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the only Sonn of God / ought to be alſo vnderſtode in aſmoche as he is God-man / and not ſimplie after his Deitie diſtinctlie conſidered / in wch regard the Apoſtle dothe not barely ſaye that God was viſible / but addeth in his fleſh. And S. Iohn confeſſeth not ſimply to have ſene the glory of the word / but ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to addeth / the worde was made fleſhe. S. Peter ſpeakinge of his fuffrings / ſayeth not ſimplie / for as moch as Chriſt hathe ſuffred: but addethe in the fleſhe / wch was nedefull for our ſalvation / becauſe he ys Man-god that ſuffred / and not ſimplie God. For a concluſion / yt ys God-man that hathe fought and ſuffred in his humanitie: and yt ys the Man-god wch hathe conquered by his Devinitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="message">
               <head>To the Anabaptiſt T.M. priſonner at Norwch.</head>
               <p>SOm loving brother ſignifie vnto hym. Fyrſt he ſo ſoddanly ſtepping from his ſpirituall mother to a new ſtepdame / reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſwete foode of the one / and lickinge vp the poyſon of the other / that therefore his ſuffringe ys as compforthleſſ as yt ys wſhe and perilouſe / not only in regard of his badd opinions / but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2684:26"/>(in iuſtifienge his horrile errors and yll cauſe of bare <hi>80.</hi> yeres continuans) he condemnethe the vniverſall churche / conſiſtinge on the faythfull Sede of Abraham in all quarters of the world / fruſtratinge the preachinge of the goſpell and Sacraments in all congregations before and after that tyme / and deprivinge all martyrs ſithens the comminge of Ieſus Chriſt frome the hope of there ſalvation / by grace and martyrdome. Wyſhinge that as he ought to diſtinguiſhe betwene true martyrdome and fauls: ſo to diſcerne betwene the ſeared conſciens from the malignant ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit / and the ſalutiferous conſciens from the holy Spirit: the one gloriouſely paintinge an evill cauſe by his ſubtill elippinge and wreſt of ſcripture / throw the wch he eubowldeneth the erringe and preſumptuouſe hart to ſuffer for error: and the other revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge the ſimple truthe by playne recorde of the worde of truthe / no leſſ rightlie illumininge / then as trulie ſanctifieng and comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortinge / humblinge and mekeninge / vntill Ioyfull and conſtant ſuffring / the voice of Gods people / being the voice of God crieng Amen to the ſame. I am in feare that he and ſuche of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen / be more infected wth arrogant knowlege / then by grace ſanctifyed wth faythfull humblenes. And let hym learne a leſſon of the penitent theyſe ſuffringe wth our ſavior: for as the one in his deſperat howldnes capled on Chriſt: ſayenge yf thow he that Chriſt / ſave thy ſelf and vs: ſo the other humbled and fearinge God rebuked hym / and there wth made ſuche a lyvely confeſſion of Chriſt to be God and man / as thoſe herpticks may tremble at Gods greate iudgements for comminge ſo ſhort / or rather to be contrarie to the ſame. Fyrſt he caulled hym Lorde / and prayed vnto hym as God the bringer of ſoules to his Kyngdom: and next he caulled hym man / ſayeng this man hathe donn nothinge worthie of death / wch was as excellent a confeſſion / as yt was a miraculouſe converſion. A rude ignorant theyfe of ſo wycked a lyfe / as moch vnacquainted wth learning as wth vertu / to make ſuche a ſownd confeſſion as yt may beſeme you and your betters to eſteme hym a holy Patterne to follow / beinge therein nothing behynd Peter and the reſt of the Apoſtles / ſo longe tyme taught of there mayſter. Wherefore two fowld preſoner / and the reſt in lyke bonds here at libertie (advowchinge that the corporall eyes and hands of the Apoſtles / ſaw and felt the incomprehencible Devinitie / and that the ſame was deade in yt ſelf and buried) I pray you tell me fyrſt in the parſon of a man conſiſtinge on a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtiall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2684:26"/>and ſpirituall ſubſtans: could ever his ſoule be eyther ſene or felt in the handlinge of hym: and will you not moche more confeſſ that the Apoſtles cowld neyther ſe nor fele the gloriouſe Devinitie of Chriſt / ſo wth houlding yt ſelf vnder the tabernacle of his bodie? next tell me what glorie / Maieſtie / brightnes / or Kyngly eſtate dyd this poore theyfe ſe wth his corporall eyes / in one ſo baſe and ſo vildly crucifyed at that tyme? he neyther ſaw that ſplendor and glory as the Apoſtles dyd at his transfigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / nor the heavens open as Iohn dyd / when Chriſt was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed: and thridly tell me / how be ſaw hym to be his Lorde and God / able to further hym to his Kyngdom and glory / who was in the ſame reproche and ignominie wth hym and his fellow? ſurely he had other clerer eyes to ſe God vnder the vayle of his fleſh / then yet ys granted to you Anabaptiſts / even ſpirituall eyes and the inward ſight of the hart. Deceyve not your ſelves in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge that you confeſſ Chriſt to be God and man / when yt ys no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo in averitie / but rather vnder a clowd: becauſe yt ys wth this addition / that he ys the celeſtiall Sede of the father / or as may deſtone ſayeth / a man come from heaven. Yf a fauls Chriſt be not fownd amonge the Anabaptiſts / I know not where ells. And what true peace of conſciens can you have in ſuffringe for ſuche a forged Chriſt / as the true Chriſt fore warnethe vs to be ware of / and not to beleve. Dare you confeſſ that the ſoule of a man (when the bodie is deade and buryed) ys a lyve as yt ys in dede and yet will blaſphemouſely ſay that the God head of Chriſt dyed when his humane nature only was ſubiect to deathe? when a man hanges on the geobet / we comprehend bothe bodie and ſoule / in ſayeng the man ys hanged / the man ys dead / or thus the man eateth / drincketh / ſlepeth / all wch ys true towching the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man: but when we ſpeake diſtinctly of the natures / then neyther dothe the ſoule dye / nor ys buried / neyther eateth / drinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth / nor ſlepeth. Further way and conſider you Anabaptiſts / whether you be the only ſpowze of Chriſt and the ſpirituall ſede of Abraham ſpecifyed to be lyke in nomber to the ſtarrs of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven / or to the duſt of the perthe? or whether to you alone and to uone other churches the graces and giftes of the holy Ghoſte were fyrſt and laſt geven ſythens Pentecoſt? or whether ſo many thowſand martyrs ſithens Chriſt his aſſention dyed in the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall fayth / or in ours? and whether yt was you that S. Iohn beheld ſo greate a multitude / wch no men could nomber of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2684:27"/>all nations that ſtode before the Lambe? yf you ſo thinck / you arrogantly err wth the papiſts and arrians / and aſmoch deceive your ſelves / as maliciouſely accuſe vs and the whole churche of God reiectinge you and your vilde opinions ſythens the fyrſt hatchinge therof by your grandſire Storck. You ſeke to encloſe the church wth in your ſtraight corners / as a childe that would lathe the whole ſea into a little hole / or as the papiſts that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſon Chriſt his Royall bodie in there wafer cake. God open your eyes.</p>
               <p>Lykewyſe you my contreymen / of another kynd and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny / removing from campion to Norden / and from thence to Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdom / and now miſerably rent / devided and ſcattered here and there:<note place="margin">Norde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> who though you howld the fundamentall poynts of our fayth wth affection to good things: yet yt ys wth an vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red zeale / vnder moch weakenes / contencions and diſcentions ioyned wth overwening and wrangling / wherby you have bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the tender reedes / quenched the ſmoking flaxe / and driven ſum into labarinthes and others into fowle errors. God touche your harts to be warned by there perrylls / and not by ſingularitie to fall wth them into ſuche errors: to be leſſ loftie / and more lowly: to eſteme better of Gods churches abowte you and to bragg leſſ of your owne / wthout Paſtor and ſacraments for theſe <hi>3.</hi> peres. And the Lorde geve you repentans / for the want of love / yeare concorde and humilitie / the lack wherof ys the cauſe you rather deſtroy then buylde / marr then make ſcatter then gather. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſe what your buſie and vnſkyllfull medling wth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline commes to: So that as yt ys not fitt for little children to handle ſharp edged tooles: evenſo as vnfitt for vnexperienced youthes / to deale wth the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of opening and ſhutting / of byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge and looſinge / and wth the ſharpe ſwerde of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: a worck more beſeminge grave and wyſe heades vnder more ſtayednes / then you of ſuche raſhenes and vnadvyſednes / mowntinge above all churches. I ſpare particularities.</p>
               <closer>The Lorde bleſſ you and vs all wth wyſdome and grace. Amen.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:2684:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
